<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters written by a French gentleman, giving a faithful and particular account of the transactions at the court of France, relating to the publick interest of Europe with historical and political reflexions on the ancient and present state of that kingdom / communicated by Monsieur Vassor.</title>
            <author>Le Vassor, Michel, 1646-1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1795</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254547</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254547</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57302</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57302)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 154:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters written by a French gentleman, giving a faithful and particular account of the transactions at the court of France, relating to the publick interest of Europe with historical and political reflexions on the ancient and present state of that kingdom / communicated by Monsieur Vassor.</title>
                  <author>Le Vassor, Michel, 1646-1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poll tax --  France.</term>
               <term>France --  Politics and government --  1643-1715.</term>
               <term>Europe --  Politics and government --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LETTERS WRITTEN BY A <hi>French</hi> GENTLEMAN, <hi>GIVING</hi> A Faithful and Particular Account of the Tranſactions at the Court of FRANCE, <hi>RELATING</hi> To the Publick Intereſt of EUROPE: WITH Hiſtorical and Political Reflexions on the Ancient and Preſent State of that KINGDOM.</p>
            <p>Communicated by Monſieur <hi>VASSOR.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed: And Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane,</hi> 1695</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Firſt Letter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>INtroduction. Page <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of ſome Conſiderations that might have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd the <hi>French King</hi> from impoſing Arbitralily a General <hi>Poll-Tax</hi> on his Subjects. Page <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Injuſtice of ſuch an <hi>Impoſition,</hi> further demonſtrated. Page <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That notwithſtanding all theſe Reaſons, the <hi>Edict</hi> for that Taxation will paſs at all adventures. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the <hi>French</hi> are tamer Slaves than either the <hi>Romans</hi> of Old, or the <hi>Danes</hi> at preſent. Page <hi>4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Motive that makes the <hi>French</hi> King endeavour to enſlave <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi> Page <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the <hi>Poll-Tax</hi> is the laſt Refuge of the <hi>French</hi> Court. Page <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Remark upon the <hi>Inſcriptions</hi> on the Gates of <hi>Paris. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the <hi>Poll-Tax</hi> will not raiſe ſuch vaſt Sums, as the Emiſſaries of that Court give out. Page <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Countrey is extreamly impoveriſhed, and the King's Revenues very much diminiſhed. Page <hi>7, 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the preſent Miſery of the <hi>French</hi> Nation is too great to admit of any Alleviation from the Proſpect of better times to come. Page <hi>9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That none dare preſume to Petition the King to Aſſemble the <hi>Eſtates</hi> of the Kingdom. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That according to the Primitive Conſtitution of the <hi>French</hi> Government, the Soveraign Authority was lodg'd in the <hi>States General</hi> of the Nation. Page <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Power of the Prince was limited among the ancient <hi>Gauls,</hi> and other Northern Nations. Page <hi>11</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57302:3"/>
               <item>That the <hi>French</hi> have ſtill a juſt Title to their ancient Priviledges. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Compariſon between the ancient and preſent condition of the <hi>Princes of the Blood,</hi> illuſtrated by ſome particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. Page <hi>12, 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of the ancient Priviledges of the <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> of <hi>France.</hi> Page <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That they had a right to oppoſe the unjuſt Deſigns of the Prince, by entering into Leagues againſt him. Page <hi>14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Hiſtory of the <hi>League of the Publick Good</hi> againſt <hi>Lewis the XI. Philip de Cominees</hi> Opinion of that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy. Page <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the ſame Cuſtom was, and is obſerved by ſeveral other Nations. Page <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the preſent <hi>Dukes</hi> and <hi>Peers</hi> of <hi>France</hi> do only enjoy a ſhadow of the Priviledges of their Anceſtors. Page <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ancient Authority of the <hi>Parliament of Paris,</hi> and of the gradual encroachments of the Crown upon it. Page <hi>18, 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Exhortation to that <hi>Body,</hi> to imitate the illuſtrious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of their Predeceſſors, and the chief Preſident <hi>la Vac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quierie</hi> under <hi>Lewis the XI.</hi> Page <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Courage of the Nation may be eaſily reviv'd by their Example. Page <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A brief view of the State of <hi>France,</hi> with relation to <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions</hi> under the Reign of ſeveral Princes. Page <hi>23, 24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of the immenſe Sums that are exacted by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the preſent King. Page <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſtupidity of the <hi>French,</hi> who ſtrive to encreaſe the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of their Oppreſſor. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Forces which the King maintain'd in time of Peace made him more terrible at <hi>Home</hi> than <hi>Abroad</hi> Page <hi>25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That his preſent numerous Armies are more fatal to his <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> than to his <hi>Neighbours. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion. Page <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:3"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THE Second Letter.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the blind Submiſſion of the <hi>Parliament of Paris</hi> to the Orders of the Court. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The preſent Miſery of the <hi>French</hi> Nation compar'd with that of the <hi>Romans</hi> under <hi>Domitian. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Account of ſome extravagant <hi>Rhodomontadoes</hi> in the Preface to the <hi>French</hi> King's late Declaration. <hi>28, 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ridiculous Vanity of that Expreſſion in it, that <hi>the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious State of</hi> France <hi>has excited the Envy of its Neighbours. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the true meaning of that <hi>Phraſe. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it was the Injuſtice of that Monarch's Attempts. that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the indignation, not the Envy of his Neighbours. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Glorious and Happy Condition of the <hi>United Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> when they were invaded by the <hi>French</hi> King. <hi>31, 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reflections on the unjuſtice of that War, and on a <hi>Solaeciſm</hi> in a Letter from the <hi>French</hi> King to the <hi>States General. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Juſtification of the <hi>Medal</hi> that was the pretended Cauſe of the War. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the Proſperity of Tyrants ought not to be call'd a <hi>Bleſſing from Heaven upon them. 34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the ſhameful Flatteries of the <hi>French Clergy,</hi> and the juſter ſentiments of the <hi>Court of Rome. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the proſperous Succeſs of the <hi>Emperor's</hi> Arms in <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi> and the impious Deſigns of the Court of <hi>France,</hi> during the Siege of <hi>Vienna. 35, 36</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57302:4"/>
               <item>That in all the Wars ſince the <hi>Pyrenaean Treaty,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King has been always the Agreſſor, and is guilty of all the Deſolations and Blood-ſhed that has been occaſion'd by them. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Difference between a <hi>Conqueror</hi> and a <hi>Robber. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the <hi>Queen's</hi> pretended Right to <hi>Brabant</hi> and <hi>Hainault,</hi> of the Validity of her Renunciation, and of the Injuſtice of the King's Irruption into the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of that Claim. <hi>39, 40.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That 'tis lawful to oppoſe a Neighbouring Prince who ſtrives to aggrandize himſelf by unjuſt Methods. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That 'twas barbarous in the King to kindle a bloody War againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> meerly upon the account of a <hi>Medal,</hi> which they alſo had taken care to ſuppreſs. <hi>42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Intolerable arrogancy of ſome <hi>Pariſian Inſcriptions. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Satyrs of the <hi>Dutch Gazettier</hi> that provok'd the Court of <hi>France. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>French</hi> King's Expedition againſt <hi>Holland,</hi> compar'd with that of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> againſt <hi>Antioch. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That it was not a Zeal for Religion that prompted the King to invade <hi>Holland. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That Subjects are obliged not to aſſiſt their Soveraign in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of an unjuſt War, prov'd out of <hi>Grotius. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That they ought even to refuſe their Aſſiſtance when the Caſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears doubtful, demonſtrated out of the ſame Author. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> King's Attempts muſt not be meaſur'd by their <hi>Succeſs. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That after all he had no Reaſon to boaſt of the <hi>Succeſs</hi> of that famous Campagne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That he ow'd his Victories to the Skill and Experience of his Generals, and not to his own Valour. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the difference between <hi>Summer-Heroes,</hi> and the pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Heroe of all Seaſons. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>That the <hi>French</hi> King acquir'd not any real and ſolid Glory at the Sieges of <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Namur. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>What Opinion after Ages will have of all his Victories and Conqueſts. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57302:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST LETTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU are pleaſed to deſire an Account of my Thoughts concerning that <hi>General Poll-Tax,</hi> with which we are threatned. And to invite me to make you the Confident of my Sentiments on this occaſion; you have ſaid enough to convince me, that I was not miſtaken in believing that you agree with me, in eſteeming it our Honour to be of the number of thoſe <hi>True Frenchmen,</hi> who continue ſtill to be Lovers of their Country. For ſo long as there ſhall be Men of Senſe and Courage in <hi>France,</hi> ſhe will ſtill retain ſome Foot-ſteps of her Dying liberty, and we ſhall ſtill preſerve the Memory of our former Priviledges. But you muſt give me leave to ask, whether you have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſider'd, how dangerouſly you expoſe both me and your ſelf, by engaging in a Correſpondence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſo nice a Subject as that of the Government. We are ſcarce allow'd the liberty to think: And what Perſecutions may we not fear, if it ſhould be diſcover'd that we have taken the freedom to ſpeak our thoughts? nevertheleſs if you have the Courage to neglect this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57302:5"/>Conſideration, I am reſolv'd not to give you occaſion to accuſe me of Cowardice; only let us endeavour to manage our Correſpondence with ſo much caution, as to hinder our Letters from being intercepted.</p>
            <p>You cannot be perſwaded to believe, that the King's Miniſters will ever adviſe him to impoſe that <hi>General Poll Tax</hi> which is ſo much talk'd of. For this, you ſay, <hi>would be no leſs than to deprive us of the only ſhadow of Liberty, that we are ſuffer'd ſtill to enjoy, What? Shall the Princes of the Blood, the Nobility? the Officers of the Crown, and all the Gentry be Tax'd like Peaſants? Shall the Clergy be Rob'd of its nobleſt Priviledge? Shall the Inhabitants of</hi> Paris, <hi>and of all the chief Cities in the Kingdom, loſe that alone of all their Rights, which they have been able to preſerve hitherto? No: the Conſequences of ſuch an Attempt are too viſible, and would be too fatal in the preſent poſture of our Affairs At leaſt,</hi> you add, <hi>it is not credible, that the King will adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Publiſh a Declaration that may open the dulleſt Eyes, and even cauſe a general Inſurrection, without calling an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meeting of the Princes of the Blood, the Peers of</hi> France, <hi>and the Officers of the Crown; and without going himſelf to the Parliament, to acquaint them with the Reaſons that oblige him to impoſe a Tax upon his Subjects, that will compleat the ſubverſion of this State, and to hear the Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances which that Wiſe and Illuſtrious Aſſembly would not fail to offer to him, on ſuch an important occaſion. This is a ſtep,</hi> you conclude, <hi>ſo contrary to the Maxims, that the King has always follow'd, ſince he began to Govern by himſelf; that they would rather endeavour to find out a Thouſand other ways to defray the Charge of the War, than reduce him to an extremity, that would vex him more than all the diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he has met with from the obſtinacy of the Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, to refuſe the Dayly Propoſals of Peace, both in General and Particular, which he cauſes to be offer'd to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57302:5"/>
            <p> I acknowledge, Sir, that your Reflexions are juſt and reaſonable; and you might have added, that the Eſtates of the Kingdom ought to have been aſſembled, and their conſent obtain'd. For if it be true what
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Philip de Cominees</hi> aſſerts, that <hi>no King or Potentate in the World has a right to exact a Penny from his Subjects, without the Advice and Conſent of thoſe that are to be Taxed, unleſs in his own Demeaſns;</hi> and that all Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions that are levied without theſe Conditions, are the effects of <hi>Tyrannical Violence:</hi> If it be true, that <hi>M. Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> and the reſt of that Tribe, who, to teſtify their Zeal and Affection to their Maſter, have perſwaded him that he has a right to all our Eſtates, <hi>have made him odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and terrible to his Neighbours, who would chuſe any Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery rather than that of being his Subjects:</hi> If it be true that there was a time when the King's of <hi>France</hi> dar'd not to ſay, <hi>I take what I will, and am Maſter of all.</hi> If all this, I ſay, be true, may we not hope that the King, who would appear to have ſo great a Senſe of Religion, will aſſemble the Eſtates of the Kingdom, to conſult with them whether it be neceſſary to continue the War, and whether it be more conducive to the publick Good, to haraſs all his own Subjects, than to do Juſtice to the Confederates.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, Sir, I can aſſure you, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Reflexions, nor mine, will hinder the King's Council from impoſing the <hi>Poll-Tax;</hi> and I'm even per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that there will not be the leaſt motion made to call a Meeting of the Princes of the Blood, the Peers of <hi>France,</hi> and Officers of the Crown; much leſs will they deſire the King to give himſelf the trouble to go in Perſon to the Parliament; and leaſt of all, will they have the Confidence to lay before him the neceſſity of ſummoning a Convention of the Eſtates. Not long ago,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57302:6"/>a certain Lady, who ſhews a wonderful concern for the Preſervation of the King's Health, grumbled at all thoſe who repreſented to the King the miſerable effects of the Famine in <hi>Paris,</hi> and other Places: She ask'd them whether they came with a deſign againſt the King's Life. And who then could be ſo hardhearted as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the King to expoſe himſelf to the danger of hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Remonſtrances of his Subjects, concerning the deplorable condition to which the Kingdom is reduc'd? This would certainly afflict the good Prince more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, and ſooner break his tender Heart, than all thoſe ſtories of his Poor languiſhing People that wander about the Streets of <hi>Paris,</hi> and are forc'd to rake the Dung-hills for Dead-Horſes, wherewith to fill their raging Stomachs.</p>
            <p>We ſtudy to imitate the Example of thoſe <hi>Romans,</hi> mentioned by
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Annal.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Tacitus,</hi> Princes, Dukes and Peers, Officers of the Crown, Biſhops, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Magiſtrates of the Sovereign Courts, and all of us together, are poſting to Slavery, and that with ſo much eagerneſs and haſte, as if we ſtrove to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run one another. We think to pleaſe the King; but I durſt ſwear that he and his Miniſter do in their Hearts hate and deſpiſe us, and that they inſult over us, as <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> over his baſe and flattering Senate, <hi>O homines ad ſervitutem paratos!</hi> There is not one amongſt us, that ever ſaw the Days of Liberty. The form and mildneſs of our Ancient Government is loſt; yet all our Care is, to flatter our Prince and to obey him blindly. We laugh at the folly of the <hi>Danes,</hi> who have diveſted themſelves of all their Liberties, and lodg'd an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power in their King's: We, I ſay, who are more ridiculouſly mad than they, who, tho' we have not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the King any one Authentick Title to our Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57302:6"/>do yet tamely ſtretch forth our Necks to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a heavier Yoke than that of the <hi>Danes,</hi> or rather a Yoke that is more cruel and inſupportable, than that which the <hi>Grand Signior</hi> and <hi>Great Mogul,</hi> impoſe upon their Slaves.</p>
            <p>At laſt the fatal time is come, in vain we expect to ſee better Days: We have put on a Chain, that will grow Dayly more inſupportable. We are not ſo much as ſuffer'd to ſpeak of Liberty, and they would hinder us too from ſeeing it enjoy'd by others. A great Man who Commanded the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies in <hi>Britain</hi> thought it neceſſary to reſolve on the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Velut é conſpectu liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas tolleretur.</hi> Tacit. <hi>in</hi> Agric.</note> leaſt the Ancient <hi>Britons,</hi> by ſeeing a free Nation ſo near them, ſhould be tempted to recover their own loſt Liberty. Is it not probable that our Court is acted by the ſame Principles? Are not theſe the Maxims that oblige her to endeavour with ſo much obſtinacy, to make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> our Companions in Slavery? She can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bear the Neighbourhood of a Nation, that has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways aſſerted its Priviledges with a great deal of Vigor; nor is ſhe leſs prejudic'd againſt another, that had the Courage to ſhake of its Fetters<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Who knows whether the <hi>French</hi> may not at laſt fall in love with the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and ſettle one like to it at Home; which after all, will be only our own Ancient form of Government reſtor'd. And
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>Philip de Cormines</hi> aſſures us, with his uſual ſincerity, that <hi>he knows not a</hi> Countrey in the World, where the Common-wealth is better manag'd, and the Subjects ſuffer leſs violence, then in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am of the ſame opinion with you, that the King wiſhes with all his Heart, he could continue the War without impoſing a <hi>General Poll-Tax;</hi> that Method is
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57302:7"/>certainly too odious to be choſen without neceſſity, and how hard and pitileſs ſoever we have found our Maſters to be, I believe they would not willingly encreaſe the Murmurings and Diſſatisfaction of the People. But what can we expect from Men that know not what courſe to take? We have ſeen enough, more than once to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us, that our Miniſters of State do not now begin to be gravel'd. The Intelligencers have no more Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs to preſent. On what then would you have them lay a new Impoſition? Would you have them Tax the Air that we breath? For that is the only Element now remains free to us.</p>
            <p>Give me leave, Sir, to put you in mind of an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, which you that have paſt ſo often through the Gates of <hi>Paris</hi> have doubtleſs made as well as I. You know that many of them bear this magnificent Inſcription,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>The happineſs of the City under</hi> Lewis <hi>the</hi> Great.</note> 
               <hi>Sub Ludovico Magno Felicitas Urbis.</hi> But if you caſt your Eye on the adjacent buildings, you ſhall find a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Toll-gatherers Houſes, on which are written, in no leſs conſpicuous Characters, the Names of Offices and Courts, for ſuch a prodigious variety of Impoſts. If you can advance further into the City, you ſhall ſcarce find a Street without an Office or Court of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, for ſome ridiculous and hitherto unheard of Taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. Such is the happineſs of the <hi>French</hi> Nation, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the long Reign of the great Prince, for whom they have erected ſo many Statues. We have not ſeen a Week theſe Six Years, that has not produc'd at leaſt One or Two new Edicts or Declarations; and at length the <hi>Invention</hi> of the ſubtleſt <hi>Finances</hi> is drain'd, as well as our Purſes. 'Tis not ſo eaſy now, as 'twas former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to find out Methods to furniſh the King with Ten, Twenty, or Thirty Millions, and a <hi>General Poll Tax</hi> is the laſt refuge.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57302:7"/>
            <p> I know not whether the very noiſe of ſo ſurpriſing a Project has not already alarm'd ſome of the <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates?</hi> 'Tis but natural for thoſe who are not well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the deplorable condition of a Countrey, that was once ſo Rich and Flouriſhing, to imagine, that this new Impoſition will make the King Maſter of a ſufficient Fund to carry on the War for ſeveral Years. And I do not at all doubt, but that the Court flatters it ſelf with the hopes of terrifying its Enemies, by the intended <hi>Declaration.</hi> Its Emiſſaries in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> will not fail to give out, that <hi>France</hi> is inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible, and that we are as able and willing to part with our Money, as the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> are to part with theirs. I am confirm'd in this Opinion, by what I heard yeſterday from one of my Friends, who inform'd me, that the ſubject of thoſe Verſes that are to be made in praiſe of the King, to obtain the Prize that is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be given by the <hi>French Acad my</hi> on <hi>St. Lewis's Day,</hi> is appointed to be this Propoſition, <hi>That the King is no leſs terrible to his Enemies by the love of his Subjects, than by the force of his Arms.</hi> For I'm ſatisfi'd, that this cannot be done without a deſign.</p>
            <p>But who will be impos'd upon by ſo obvious a trick, or regard ſo baſe and ridiculous a piece of flattery? Are the <hi>Confederates</hi> ignorant of the general Diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Nobility, Gentry, and Third Eſtate, which is ſo apparent in <hi>Paris,</hi> and all the Towns in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom? Have they not heard in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> that the King's Revenues are conſiderably diminiſhed? And thô the Truth of this were not ſo publickly known, it would not require a very great ſtock of Sagacity to Divine, that they, who have not Money to buy Bread, cannot be ſuppoſed to conſume much Wine, either at Home or at the Tavern; and that conſequently the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57302:8"/>Entries at <hi>Paris,</hi> and in the other Cities of <hi>France,</hi> do not now amount to ſuch great Sums as they did hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The Peaſants are generally ſo miſerable, that they are not able to fetch Salt from the Garner, from whence 'tis likewiſe plain, that the King's Coffers are not ſo well fill'd by the <hi>Gabels</hi> as formerly they were. The Fields lie until'd, and are almoſt turn'd to Deſarts: An infinite number of People are Dead of Hunger, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, and other Epidemical Diſtempers. Thoſe Towns which we have ſeen in a flouriſhing condition and well Peopled, are ruin'd and abandon'd by their Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, and moſt of the Labourers and Tradeſmen are reduc'd to Beggery; wonder not then, that the King is forc'd to Tax the Princes, Gentry, Clergy, and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of free Cities, ſince there are ſo few others left to be Tax'd.</p>
            <p>Uut you will perhaps tell me, that we do not now begin to be Tax'd; for, you'll ſay, we contributed to pay all thoſe Taxations, which were exacted from our Farmers and Labourers; ſince we might have let out our Lands to better Advantage, if our Tenants had not been Tax'd: And conſequently the Priviledges of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Clergy, and Inhabitants of <hi>Paris,</hi> and other Cities, are no more than imaginary Titles. What then, Sir? Did not the King become the moſt glorious and powerful Monarch in the World, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing only the
<note n="*" place="margin">That which was paid by the Farmers.</note> 
               <hi>Real</hi> Taxation upon us? And ſhall we grudge to Pay a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal</hi> Tax for the Preſervation of all that Glory and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, which he has ſo juſtly acquir'd at the Charge of his good Subjects. Alas! Sir, ſhall we ſuffer all theſe fine Inſcriptions to be defac'd, with which the <hi>Place de Viatoire,</hi> and the Gates of <hi>St. Denis</hi> and <hi>St. Martin</hi> are adorn'd.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57302:8"/>
            <p> But this is not a time for Mirth; If our King's aſſume a Power to impoſe a <hi>General Poll-Tax</hi> as often as the fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy takes them, you may aſſure your ſelf, that it will take them oftner then we deſire. This is the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mark of our Servitude; the <hi>French</hi> Nation has loſt both its Honour and its Liberty; neither can I think of any Remedy for ſo cruel a Diſaſter. Let us try the Virtue of thoſe Maxims that we find in our dear <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ulterior a mirari, praeſentiae ſ qui.</hi> Tacit. <hi>Hiſtor. l.</hi> 4.</note>
               <q>A Wiſe Man, ſays he, may admire the Happineſs of former Ages; but he bears preſent Misfortunes with Patience.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bonos Imperatores volo expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere; qualeſcunque tolerare.</hi> Idem.</note> We ought to wiſh for good Princes, but muſt bear with ſuch as we have.
<note n="¶" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ut Steriltatem &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>imios Imbres &amp; caetera Naturae mala, ita Luxum vel Avaritiam Dominantium tolerate; 8. d ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que haec con inua, &amp; meliorum interventu penſantur.</hi> Idem.</note> The Reign of a bad Prince is like a Year of Dearth and Famine; and our Miſeries in this World are not Eternal. </q>For as the next good Year makes amends for our former loſſes; ſo a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant is ſometimes ſucceeded by a good Prince. Thus we may comfort our ſelves with hopes of better times under the <hi>Dauphin;</hi> theſe Maxims, I confeſs are not very proper to ſatisfie Men in our circumſtances; but they are the beſt that I am able to ſuggeſt to you.</p>
            <p>Shall we entreat the King to call a general Meeting of the Eſtates of the Realm? But who will undertake to preſent our Petition to him? Shall the Princes of the Blood? There is not one among them that durſt offer the leaſt Remonſtrance to His Majeſty; ſhall the Dukes and Peers of <hi>France,</hi> or the Officers of the Crown? They might expect to be immediatly rewarded with a lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the <hi>Baſtile;</hi> and there are too many baſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57302:9"/>with the Times, who would offer their Service to drag them thither. Shall thoſe of the Firſt Order in the Church? The Court has found out a way to make ſure of them; the Clergy has contributed already vaſt Sums, and 'tis ſaid, that ſeveral Millions more will be demanded of them ſhortly; Should the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> deliver our Addreſs, they would inſtantly be interdicted, and the Heads of that Aſſembly would be puniſhed as ſeditious Traytors? ſhould it be preſented by the Inhabitants of <hi>Paris,</hi> and the reſt of the great Cities, we ſhould ſee Gibbets erected in every corner of the Streets, and the Troops of the <hi>Houſhold</hi> ſent to devour 'em: Our Poor and Ill-paid Officers would bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly pillage the Houſes of thoſe Perſons, who could be accus'd of no other Crime, than of endeavouring to preſerve that little remainder of Liberty which they ſeem ſtill to enjoy.</p>
            <p>I had the fortune, ſome Days ago, to be in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, where they talk'd variouſly concerning the late Revolution in <hi>England.</hi> A Man of Senſe, who is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well acquainted with the Ancient and Modern Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> demonſtrated plainly, that our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was formerly like to that of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Sovereign Authority was properly lodg'd in the <hi>Meeting of the Eſtates.</hi> There Laws were made; there the moſt important Caſes were decided, and ſuch Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies as were judg'd neceſſary for the Defence of the Kingdom were granted; the King had no more Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than what was ſufficient to enable him to cauſe the Decrees of thoſe Aſſemblies te be put in Execution, and to attend diligently to the Security and Preſervation of the State. Theſe are obvious Remarks, which every one that reads our Ancient Hiſtories, thô but with a very moderate degree of Application, cannot fail to obſerve.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57302:9"/>
            <p> Such were, in effect, the inviolable Maxims of the <hi>Gauls,</hi> and of the Northern Nations, from whom both we and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are deſcended.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Servirent Syria,</hi> Aſiaque, <hi>&amp; ſuetus Regibus</hi> Oriens, <hi>multos adhuc in</hi> Gallia <hi>vivere ante tributa genitos.</hi> Tacit. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 4.</note>
               <q>Let the People of the Eaſt, who are accuſtom'd to the Deſpotic Government of their Kings, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoke, ſaid a great Man among our <hi>Gauls,</hi> we will not follow their Example, We can ſtill remember a time when we paid no Tribute.
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Libertatem Naturâ mutis Animalibus datam; virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem proprium hominum bonum.</hi> Idem. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> Nature made the Beaſts free, as well as Men, with this only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, That Men are endued with Virtue and Courage to preſerve their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</q> The <hi>Hollanders</hi> have not yet forgot the Heroical ſentiments of their <hi>Country-man;</hi> but we, alas! loſe the Memory of 'em Dayly.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec Regibus infinita aut li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera poteſtas.</hi> Tacit. <hi>de mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus</hi> Germanorum.</note>
               <q>The Northern Nations never ſuffer'd their King's to aſſume an Arbitrary and unlimited Power;
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auctoritate ſuadendi magis quam juben<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i poteſtate.</hi> Idem. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> their Princes govern rather by Perſwaſion, than Force:
<note n="¶" place="margin">
                     <hi>Regnantur paulo addictius, quam ceterae</hi> Germanorum <hi>gentes, nondum tamen ſupra libertatem.</hi> Idem. <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </note> And even ſuch of thoſe Nations as were under the ſevereſt Government, did ſtill enjoy a great deal of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To all theſe Obſervations, my Friend added one more, that ſince we have not like the <hi>Danes,</hi> renounc'd our Liberty, we may lawfully endeavour to ſhake off the Yoke that is impoſed upon us. For there is no juſt Preſcription againſt the fundamental Laws of a State. But how reaſonable ſoever theſe Remarks be, they appear ſo new and ſo ſurpriſing to certain Perſons,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57302:10"/>that they imagine it to be no leſs ridiculous to talk of aſſembling the Eſtates at this time of the Day, than it would be to perſwade them to reſume the Ruff and Bonets that were uſed in the time of <hi>Francis the Firſt.</hi> Theſe are obſolete Stories, ſay they, and we do not ſo much as remember, that ever there were Eſtates in <hi>France.</hi> 'Tis true, replied one of our Friends angri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we forgot that we are <hi>French-men,</hi> and we ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get too e'er long, that we are reaſonable Men.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romans,</hi> ſaid one of their own Emperors,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nec totam ſervitutem pati poſſunt, nec totam libertatem</hi> Tacit. <hi>Hiſt. lib.</hi> 1.</note> are no longer capable of enjoying a full and entire Liberty, thô they were again put in poſſeſſion of it, nor will they bear too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy a Yoke; is it poſſible, that we ſhould be already, more accuſtom'd to Slavery, than a People that had ſerv'd ſuch Maſters as <hi>Tiberius, Caligula,</hi> and <hi>Nero?</hi> I'm perſwaded the King will never give ſuch advice to the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> as <hi>Galba</hi> did to him whom he thought to make his Succeſſor. No care will be taken to ſweeten our Bondage, we are ſuch tame Slaves, that Policy would be loſt upon us.</p>
            <p>The Princes of the Blood are by their Birth chief Counſellors of State; their Advice ought to be taken on all occaſions that relate to the Intereſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſuch as the making of War and Peace, entering into Leagues, raiſing of Subſidies, and the like. It were eaſy to prove this by our Hiſtories, and by the Edicts of our King's. But now the Face of Affairs is altered; and nothing of moment is imparted to theſe. They are too happy when His Majeſty ſuffers them to paſs ſome idle and tedious Hours at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> or to go to the Camp to be kill'd like private Soldiers. Not only matters of State are not communicated to them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:57302:10"/>but they are not ſuffer'd to be Maſters even at home, nor ſo much as conſulted concerning the Marriage of their own Children. 'Tis well known after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the Duke of <hi>Chartres</hi> married Mademoiſelle <hi>de Blois.</hi> The Prince, to preſerve an Office and a Government in his Family, and to ſecure the Fortunes of his Children, was forc'd to marry them to Baſtards, whoſe Mother's Name would not be permitted to be mentioned in any publick Deed.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Conty</hi> is Maſter of all thoſe excellent Endowments both natural and acquired, with which a Perſon of his Quality ought to be adorn'd: But what Treatment does ſo rare a Merit procure him at the Court? He is left without Command, Office, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; while the chief Employments are given to to thoſe that are infinitely beneath him. I know ſome Gentlemen who are oftentimes wont to complain, that the Princes of the Blood are not more tenderly touch'd with a ſence of their own Diſgrace, and our Miſeries. But neither is their Power conſiderable, nor do we me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit their Aſſiſtance. The late Prince, inſpired with a juſt Indignation againſt the <hi>French</hi> Nobility, uſed to ſay, <hi>I put the Sword in their Hands, I cry'd out againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and they anſwered me with Muſquet-ſhot.</hi> The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his Misfortunes has taught our Princes Caution: And if any one among 'em ſhould have the Generoſity to declare himſelf the Protector of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt, who could aſſure us that our Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men would not ſtill be Fools enough to fight againſt him?</p>
            <p>The Dukes and Peers, and Officers of the Crown, are likewiſe, by vertue of their Dignity, chief Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of State, and have a Right to go to the Parliament when they pleaſe. Ah! vain Shadow of the Glorious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57302:11"/>Priviledges of the ancient Peers of <hi>France.</hi> No matter of Importance was tranſacted without their Conſent. They remain'd unconcern'd Spectators of the Wars that were begun without their Approbation, leaving the King to purſue his own private Quarrels, and ſerv'd him only in thoſe Wars which they judg'd neceſſary for the common good of the Realm. Such is the obedience which the preſent Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> pay to the Emperor; and you know better than I, that the Government of <hi>France</hi> did very much reſemble that of <hi>Germany,</hi> before our King's had remitted to the Crown thoſe great Fiefs, that were diſmembred from it, during the Reign of <hi>Hugh Capet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the King acted contrary to the Priviledges of the Nobility, or to the good of the People, they did not fail to oppoſe him; they appeal'd to the States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>General, and enter'd into Leagues among themſelves, and with the principal Cities, to prevent the Execution of the unjuſt attempts of their Prince. <hi>Philip</hi> Sirnam'd the Long, had form'd a deſign to ſeize on the fifth part of the Eſtates of his Subjects, under the pretext of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming or New-coining the Money. <hi>But the Princes and the Prelates,</hi> ſays
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abridgement of</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeray.</note> one of our Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rians, <hi>would not ſuffer the King's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries to Execute his Orders; they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal'd to the States General, and enter'd into Confederacies with the Cities, which had ſo good an effect, that the Impoſition could not be Levied.</hi> Do you think that theſe generous Patriots would have ſuffer'd a King to ſeize on the fifth part of all the Coin'd Money in the Kingdom twice in leſs than Four Years, by commanding it Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily to be new Stamp'd? And when did we renounce our Right of having recourſe to thoſe means which our Anceſtors might lawfully make uſe of, for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Eſtates and Liberties?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57302:11"/>
            <p> No ſooner had <hi>Lewis XI.</hi> mounted the Throne, but he began to
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abridgement of</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeray.</note> 
               <hi>Govern without a Council, and for the moſt part alſo without Juſtice and Reaſon. He fancyed himſelf an abler Politician than his Predeceſſors, and left no means uneſſay'd to make himſelf terrible. He choſe rather to follow the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of his own unruly Humour, than to obſerve the Wiſe Laws of the Nation. He thought he could not make a nobler uſe of his Authority, than by oppreſſing his Subjects, and that the beſt way to diſplay his Grandeur, was by ruining the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Families in the Kingdom, and advancing the meaneſt of the People. This is what ſome call,</hi> ſays <hi>Mezeray, to paſs the Mon-age of Royalty, and to rule without a Tutor, but they ought rather to ſay, without Senſe or Reaſon.</hi> Thus the King, by endeavouring to aſſume an Arbitrary or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick Power, irritated the Minds of the Princes of the Blood, the Nobility, and all true Lovers of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, who reſolv'd generouſly to ſhake off the Yoke that they were not accuſtom'd to bear. <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and firſt Prince of the Blood, undertook to repreſent their grievances to His Majeſty, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a numerous Aſſembly of Perſons of Quality who were met at the Court. Accordingly he ſpoke to the King with all the freedom that <hi>his Age, Reputation, and Quality Authoriſed him to uſe: But theſe Remonſtrances offended His Majeſty, and were received with Indignation and Scorn,</hi> adds the ſame
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abridgement of</hi> Mezeray.</note> Hiſtorian. The good Duke Died with Grief, two Days after: But not long after the King's Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Count of <hi>Charolois</hi> Son of the Duke of <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundy,</hi> the Dukes of <hi>Bretaign, Calabria, Bourbon,</hi> and <hi>Alenzon,</hi> with ſeveral other Princes of the Blood, the Duke of <hi>Vemours,</hi> the Counts of <hi>Armaguac, Dunois, S. Pol,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de Lohear,</hi> the Lords of <hi>Albret,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57302:12"/>Bueil,</hi> and <hi>Chaumont-Amboiſe,</hi> and almoſt all the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and old Officers of the Army enter'd into an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation to oppoſe the pernicious Deſigns of the King: And this Confederacy was call'd the <hi>League of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick-Good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> was then reduc'd to ſo great an extremity, that if the City of <hi>Paris</hi> had joyn'd with the League, they might have eaſily driven him out of the Kingdom. Our flatterers are wont to call this Confederacy an unlawful Rebellion. But <hi>Philip de Cominees</hi> did not think fit to give it ſo odious a name; he was better acquainted with the Rights both of the Subjects and Sovereigns of <hi>Europe.</hi> Far from that, he only blames the United Princes for neglecting to ſecure the Intereſts of the People, when they made their own Peace with the King.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Publick Good,</hi> ſays he, <hi>yielded to private Intereſt.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Abridgement of</hi> Mezeray.</note> A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Hiſtorian adds, that it was agreed to nominate <hi>Thirty and Six Perſons, whom they called</hi> Notables, <hi>conſiſting of an equal number of the Nobility, Clergy, and Lawyers, who ſhould be impowered to conſult together, and to fall upon proper Methods to eaſe the People of their Grievances, and to redreſs the diſorders of the State.</hi> This inſtance gives us a clear view of the ancient Cuſtoms and Liberties of <hi>France,</hi> before it was enſlav'd by the pernicious Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of <hi>Mazarin, le Tellier, Colbert, Lowvois,</hi> and the reſt of that baſe and mercenary Gang, who have ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic'd the Honour and Priviledges of their Country, to their private Intereſt and Ambition. But we have, at leaſt, the Comfort to ſee that their Children and Heirs begin to deteſt ſuch damnable Politicks, ſince the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of theſe ſubtle Miniſters are ruin'd, in purſuance of thoſe very Counſels which were firſt given by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57302:12"/>
            <p> I have alaeady ſaid that <hi>Philip de Cominees</hi> was too well acquainted with the Priviledges both of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> to condemn the Members of the Confederacy that was ſet on foot againſt <hi>Lewis the XIth,</hi> as Rebels againſt their lawful Sovereign. For it muſt not be imagin'd, that the Cuſtom of entering into Aſſociation againſt Tyrannical Princes, was peculiar to <hi>France.</hi> It was univerſally claim'd as their undoubted Right by all thoſe States that were founded by the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Nations, on the Ruins of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. The Princes, Biſhops, and free Cities of <hi>Germany,</hi> have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways retain'd, and do to this very Day continue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their undoubted Priviledge, to make Leagues againſt the Emperor, in defence of their Rights and Liberties. The ſame Cuſtom was alſo obſerv'd by the ancient <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and even own'd by their King's: For when they agreed on certain Articles with the Peers of the Kingdom, it was concluded on both ſides, that the Nobility had a right to maintain their Prerogatives by force of Arms, in caſe the King ſhould attempt to violate them. And it is no leſs certain, that the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, Biſhops, and principal Cities of <hi>Spain,</hi> have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd the ſame Priviledge, when they judg'd it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the good of their Countrey. It were eaſy to prove this by many and clear inſtances; but I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf with putting you in mind of the League which they made under the Reign of <hi>Charles the V,</hi> call'd <hi>la Junta Samta,</hi> to deliver themſelves from the Tyranny of the <hi>Flemings,</hi> to whom that Prince had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted the Government of his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>The Grandees of that Kingdom do ſtill maintain their Prerogatives, without ſuffering them to be violated; and ſhall we be the only Slaves in <hi>Europe?</hi> Shall our Nobility ſo fam'd of old for their Bravery, and that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57302:13"/>Warlike and undaunted Spirit which diſtinguiſhed them with ſo much advantage in the World, or rather ſhall their degenerated Poſterity, inſtead of attempting to regain their ancient Liberty, tamely ſuffer themſelves to be kill'd, and Dayly offer'd up as ignoble Victims to ſupport that Arbitrary Power that oppreſſes them? 'Tis true, a Duke and Peer of <hi>France</hi> may enter into the <hi>Louvre</hi> in his Coach, and ſit for faſhion's ſake on the <hi>Flower-de-luces</hi> in the <hi>Grand-chamber,</hi> and has alſo the pleaſure to ſee a ſtool preſented to his Lady, when ſhe comes to attend the Queen: And are not theſe mighty Priviledges, or rather the Poor remainders of all that Honour and Authority that adorn'd the prime Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of ſo great a Kingdom.</p>
            <p>But perhaps the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> are better Judges of the true Intereſt of the Nation. I do not at all doubt, but that there are ſome intelligent and well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Magiſtrates in that numerous body, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand perfectly the Rights both of the People and of the Prince, who bewail our Miſeries, and deſire nothing more ardently, than to be able to contribute ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more than bare wiſhes to regain our ancient Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties; but they dare not diſcover their true ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I am confident, you will not think your time ill-employ'd in Reading an Account of that Aſſembly, for which I am oblig'd to one of my Friends, who is a Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Our Parliament, ſaid he, is now no more than a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of wrangling Practitioners in Law, who ſtudy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Cuſtoms, Edicts, and Proceedings of Courts. It was at firſt inſtituted to repreſent the States General of the Kingdom: It was a Body compoſed of the ſix chief Peers of <hi>France,</hi> the ſix Eccleſiaſtical Peers, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, Principal Officers of the Crown, and ſome other Perſons of Note who had a Right to ſit in the States-General,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57302:13"/>when the Neceſſity of Affairs required their Meeting. They maintain'd the Intereſts of the People againſt the Uſurpations of the Prince, &amp; ſhared the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Authority with him, when the States were not aſſembled. For 'tis beyond Controverſie certain, that the Parliament uſed to judge even the Peers and greateſt Perſons in the Kingdom, that they tender'd the Oath of Fidelity to the Officers of the Crown, and that the King's Edicts were never reputed to have the Force of Laws, nor could be put in execution till they had been firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd and regiſter'd in that Aſſembly: And are not theſe the moſt certain and unconteſted Marks of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reignty?</p>
            <p>You know, continued the Preſident, by what dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Methods, and under what ſpecious pretexts, our King's have made ſuch great Alterations in a Company that ey'd them too near, and often troubled them. 'Tis true indeed, that 'tis long ſince the Parliament began to be wholly taken up in hearing and determining Civil and Criminal Cauſes; but they ſtill enjoy'd that Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge undiſputed, which authoriſed them to examine the Edicts that the King intended to Publiſh; they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred ſuch of them as they thought uſeful and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and if at any time they met with ſome difficulties, they offer'd their Reaſons to the King, who never us'd to neglect them, but when he had a mind to proceed to violent Methods. I confeſs the Court has ſometimes compell'd 'em to Regiſter its Edicts, but then they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail'd to enter a Proteſtation that ſuch inſtances ſhould not be made uſe of to juſtify future Violences, but where are all our Priviledges now? The King, indeed, ſends his Edicts to us, but we are obliged to regiſter them as ſoon as they are ſent, and even ſuch of them that appear to our Conſciences to be highly unjuſt and pernicious,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57302:14"/>without daring to offer the leaſt Remonſtrance to his Majeſty. We have no more Power than ſimple Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey Judges, and the Edict for the <hi>Poll-Tax</hi> will paſs at all Adventures.</p>
            <p>All that you have ſaid is certainly true, reply'd I to the Magiſtrate, but will you not ſhow the leaſt ſign of Life in a Caſe of ſuch vaſt Importance? And muſt we never expect that you will be moved to make at leaſt one glorious Effort to deliver your Countrey from Tyranny and Oppreſſion? Moſt willingly, cry'd my generous Friend, with Tears in his Eyes: But are you acquainted with the King's Humour? The Times are chang'd, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered I, and we are undone. Remember the Illuſtrious example of the firſt Preſident <hi>la Vacquerie. Lewis XI.</hi> ſent an unjuſt Edict to the Parliament, which they generouſly refus'd to enroll; he renew'd his Orders, but without ſhaking their Conſtancy. At laſt the incenſt Prince, fell into a Fury, and threatned to put to Death not only the Preſident, but all the Councellors, if they perſiſted in their Obſtinacy. <hi>La Vacquerie</hi> acquainted his Brethern with the King's Menaces; and theſe good Magiſtrates having put on their Habits of Ceremony, went all in a body to the <hi>Louvre.</hi> The King ſurpris'd to ſee his Parliament come to pay him a viſit with ſo much ſolemnity, ask'd ſuddenly, what brought them thither—.</p>
            <p>I know all the ſtory, ſaid my Friend, interrupting me haſtily, and can tell you the chief Preſident's An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; we come, Sir, ſaid he to the King, to offer our Heads to Your Majeſty; ſince our Conſcience will not permit us to Regiſter the Edict which you ſent to us: Very well, reply'd I, but how did that cruel and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince receive ſo unexpected a Compliment? He diſſembled his Anger, and endeavoured to pacify their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57302:14"/>Minds by aſſuring them, that he would never deſire them to enroll any Edict contrary to the Laws of the Kingdom, or the Intereſt of his Subjects. Why then will not you adventure to make a like Attempt? I'm per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the King would be ſtrangely daunted, if the chief Preſident, at the Head of the Parliament, ſhould entertain him with a lively and paſſionate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of the deplorable condition of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. But I had forgotten that you have long ago ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſted all your eloquence in writing Panegyricks on <hi>our invincible Monarch.</hi> 'Tis pity that you have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd ſome part of it for Diſcourſes of another nature, which would certainly be more ſeaſonable at this time of the Day. Be not cruel to your Friends, anſwer'd the Preſident; We do all that we are able to do, but we are not under the Reign of a <hi>Lewis XI</hi> In thoſe Days the Nobility and People of <hi>France</hi> had not loſt all their Courage, and the Court dreaded the effects of it. I acknowledge that, replyed I, but are you ſure that the King would not treat you with as much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance, if you ſpoke to him with the ſame vigour, and ſhow'd your ſelves capable of enlivening the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numm'd Spirits of our Countreymen. Believe me, Mr. Preſident, the King deſpiſes you for your Cowardiſe; and you might make the Court tremble in its turn, if you had the Courage to imitate your Predeceſſors. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe words, we laid aſide Politicks, and began to talk of other Matters.</p>
            <p>Yes, Sir, I am ſtill of the ſame opinion: I know that the Inhabitants of <hi>Paris,</hi> and our other Cities, are extreamly diſpirited; but I dare be bold to anſwer for them, that they would quickly reſume their former Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, if the Princes of the Blood, the Nobility or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Paris</hi> would give them the leaſt encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57302:15"/>They begin to murmur ſtrangely, and I know not whether all their Patience be not already exhauſted. 'Tis true, the flatterers of the Court have bellow'd in their Ears ſo long, that <hi>The King is Maſter of all the Eſtates of his Subjects,</hi> that the poor People ſeem in good earneſt to give credit to the moſt deteſtable Lie that ever was invented. But how eaſily will they be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceiv'd, when it ſhall be made appear to them, what our ſubtle Miniſters have ſo induſtriouſly hid from them, that Taxes and Subſidies were formerly Levied in <hi>France,</hi> as they are in <hi>England,</hi> and that we never reſign'd our ancient Priviledges.</p>
            <p>You remember, Sir, when I had the pleaſure to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your Converſation in that ſolitary but delightful place, whither you have choſen to retire, that we ſpent part of our time in reading the Hiſtory of <hi>France,</hi> and that we could not find that any Impoſitions were laid upon the People before the Reign of <hi>Philip the Fair.</hi> Our King's in thoſe Days had no ſtanding Forces, but the Nobility ſerv'd them at their own charge in thoſe Wars, that were made with the conſent of the States-General. If ever any of our Princes rais'd a Subſidy by way of <hi>Taxation,</hi> it was only when the preſſing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of his Affairs conſtrain'd him to take that Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and the <hi>Tax</hi> was Levied but once. And even on ſuch urgent occaſions, thoſe Monarchs that had any ſenſe of Humanity or Religion, were very loath to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to ſo rough an expedient. The good <hi>St. Lewis,</hi> by his Teſtament, enjoin'd his Children not to Tax their Subjects; but, Alas! they who boaſt of their deſcent from ſo Juſt, ſo Chaſte, and ſo Religious a Prince, have no more regard to the good Advice that he left them, than they have to the Virtuous example of his Life.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57302:15"/>
            <p> His Nephew attempted to raiſe the Hundred and fiftieth <hi>Denier</hi> of the Revenues of his Subjects. But what was the event? <hi>Paris, Rouen,</hi> and <hi>Orleans,</hi> revolted, the Commiſſioners appointed to gather the Taxation were kill'd, and the King was forc'd to diſſemble his Indignation. Nor was <hi>Philip the Fair</hi> more ſucceſsful in his ſecond attempt, to lay an Impoſition of Six <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niers</hi> in the <hi>Livre</hi> on the ſale of Commodities; his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders were univerſally contemn'd, and he was forc'd to call a Meeting of the States General at <hi>Paris,</hi> to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue them himſelf, and repreſent to them the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his Affairs, after which he obtain'd his deſire.</p>
            <p>The ſucceeding Princes obſerv'd the ſame Method. Sometimes on urgent occaſions, <hi>Aids,</hi> and <hi>extraordinary Subſidies</hi> were Granted, but were never made perpetual, but by the Authority of the States. The King could not augment thoſe perpetual Subſidies that were grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, and far leſs could he impoſe new ones. The Court Paraſites made it their buſineſs to perſwade <hi>Lewis XI,</hi> that it was a branch of his Prerogative to lay what Impoſitions he pleas'd on his Subjects. I have already told you what <hi>Philip de Comines</hi> thinks of this Maxim. We have at leaſt as much Reaſon to complain of <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> now, as the Subjects of that Prince had in thoſe Days; but our Tongues are ty'd. <hi>Charles VII</hi> was engag'd in a long and chargeable War againſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> yet he never Levied above <hi>Eighteen hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Livres per Annum.</hi> 'Tis true, <hi>Lewis XI.</hi> augmented the Impoſitions, to <hi>Three Millions and Seven hundred thouſand Livres Tearly,</hi> but he had the Character of a very bad Prince, and to ſay all in one word, a Tyrant. His Son <hi>Charles VIII</hi> fearing to meet with the ſame Fate, and deſirous to <hi>live according to the Commandments of God,</hi> ſays <hi>Philip de Comines,</hi> reſolv'd <hi>to content himſelf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57302:16"/>with the Crown-lands, together with the Sum of Twelve hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Livres, which the Eſtates aſſembled at</hi> Tours, <hi>had granted him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> was happy under the Reign of <hi>Lewis XII,</hi> who was call'd the <hi>Father of the People,</hi> whence we may reaſonably infer, that the Face of Affairs is wonderfully chang'd ſince that time. Under the late King <hi>Lewis XIII,</hi> the Impoſitions amounted to near <hi>Fourſcore Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions,</hi> of which not above <hi>Five and Thirty</hi> were brought into the Treaſury, the reſt being exhauſted by the great charges of the Scate. <hi>M. Colbert</hi> has found means to raiſe the King's Revenues to <hi>One hundred and Twenty Millions</hi> and upwards. This could not be done without ruining an infinite number of Families by impoſing a prodigious number of new Taxations, beſides the enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous augmentation of thoſe that were already eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed. Now if <hi>One hundred and Twenty Millions</hi> be brought Yearly into the King's Coffers, the total Sum of the Impoſitions muſt amount at leaſt to <hi>One hundred and Fifty,</hi> the charges of the State being infinitely aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented ſince the beginning of the preſent War: And we ſhall quickly ſee them riſe to <hi>Two hundred,</hi> for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all, <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> cannot ſubſiſt under a <hi>Hundred Millions per Annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet we have patience enough to ſuffer all theſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries: but what do I talk of Patience and Suffering? No; we admire them, we delight in them, and fancy them to be the greateſt glories of our Nation. The King, we cry, is the greateſt Monarch in <hi>Europe:</hi> All other Princes are meer Beggars, and miſerable Wretches. He has Ten thouſand Men in the Troops of his Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould; in time of Peace he maintains a Hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men in Garriſons, to preſerve all thoſe fine Towns that he has Conquer'd and Fortified: At preſent, Three
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57302:16"/>hundred thouſand Men Fight under his Banners againſt all the Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> that are united againſt him. Incorrigible Sots that we are! that numerous, and magnificent Train of the King's Houſhold; thoſe Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand Men whom he maintains in time of Peace; that prodigious Army of Three hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men, who obey his Orders during the War, and that vaſt number of ſtrong and well Man'd Garriſons; what do all theſe things ſignifie to us? To devour us, to enthral us, and to make us odious to all <hi>Europe.</hi> Have we not Reaſon to think our Money well beſtow'd.</p>
            <p>The Forces that the King kept on Foot in time of Peace, made him more terrible at home than abroad. Theſe Domeſtick Enemies made us ſuffer our ſelves to be oppreſt Daily with new Edicts, without reſiſtance, and forc'd us to be ſilent ſpectators when the Nobility were rob'd of their Priviledges, and the Cities depriv'd of their ancient Rights. The Noblemen have ruin'd themſelves by their Luxury, and by that chargeable way of living, into which they have been ſo ſubtlely engag'd. Our Cities have not Canon to defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; their great Guns were taken from them under pretext of ſending them to the Frontiers. They are open and defenceleſs, and even are not ſuffer'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair their decay'd Walls. 'Tis enough for them to erect Statues for the King, or to cauſe Inſcriptions to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grav'd in Honour of that <hi>Immortal Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Fortifications and numerous Garriſons of <hi>Cazal, Stratbourg,</hi> and other frontier places, have drain'd the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of prodigious Sums of Money; and what advantage does it receive from them, but that they have made them jealous of us, and incenſt our Neighbours againſt us. That Army of Three hundred thouſand Men exhauſts all the Men and Money in the Kingdom. All the People turn
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57302:17"/>Soldiers; and perhaps the conſequences of a Peace would be more fatal to us, than the War. What muſt be done with all that Army after the publication of a Peace, which is ſo much long'd for, and which we might quickly enjoy, if the King would do Juſtice to his Neighbours, and to his Subjects. The Allies ſeem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to force him to do Juſtice to them: And we might be in a condition to demand Juſtice from him in ſuch a manner, that he durſt not refuſe it, if the force of his Arms which is ſo loudly celebrated by our Orators and Poets, were not more fatal to us than to our Neighbours.</p>
            <p>Let us conclude from all that has been ſaid, for 'tis time to put an end to a Letter that is already too long, let us conclude, I ſay, that the <hi>Poll-Tax</hi> will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, becauſe we have made ourſelves Slaves, and are eyen fond of our Chains, Adieu: I wiſh you as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a new Year, as you can poſſibly enjoy in ſuch dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricult time, and ſo deſolate a Countrey.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 2 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57302:17"/>
            <head>THE SECOND LETTER.</head>
            <p>AT laſt, Sir, the Court has convinc'd us, that ſhe can be <hi>as good as her Word;</hi> and that we may believe her when ſhe <hi>threatens,</hi> whatever Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we may have to ſuſpect the ſincerity of her <hi>Promiſes.</hi> On the 18th inſtant, the King by his Edict commanded a <hi>General Poll-Tax</hi> to be Levied throughout the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, as you may ſee by the Copy of the <hi>Declaration</hi> which I have ſent you; and Three Days after it was Regiſtred in the Parliament. This effect of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance does not at all ſurprize me; they have been for ſeveral Years a ſtanding example of blind ſubmiſſion to the Orders of the Court; and at laſt they have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed their obedience ſo far, that we may with a great deal of juſtice apply to our ſelves, that which our good Friend <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid of his own Age.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sicut vetus aetas vidit quid ultimum in libertate eſſet, it a nos quid in Servitute</hi> Tacit. <hi>in</hi> Agric.</note> Our Anceſtors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the laſt moments of expir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Liberty under the Miniſtry of Cardinal <hi>Richlieu;</hi> and we are forc'd to ſuffer the laſt and utmoſt rigours of Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57302:18"/>
            <p> The Age of <hi>Domitian</hi> was an exact model of ours;
<note n="*" place="margin">Adempto per inquiſitiones loquendi audiendique commer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio.</note> we dare neither complain our ſelves, nor hear the complaints of others:
<note n="†" place="margin">Memoriam quoque ipſam cum voce perdidiſſemus, ſi tam in noſtra poteſtate eſſet obliviſci, quum tacere.</note> And we ſhould have already loſt even the <hi>Memory</hi> of our former happineſs, as well as our <hi>Voice;</hi> if we could as eaſily <hi>forget</hi> as be <hi>ſilent.</hi> But we ſhall not, by my conſent, be altogether ſuch tame Slaves as theſe <hi>Romans:</hi> Let us at leaſt have the courage to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that under the former Reigns we oblig'd even our haughtieſt and moſt ambitious Monarchs to ſuffer
<note n="*" place="margin">Res olim diſſociabiles prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatum &amp; libertatem.</note> Liberty to ſubſiſt with Sovereignty; for we need only caſt our Eyes upon <hi>England</hi> to be convinc'd, that theſe two things are not incompatible; and let us not be afraid to tell our Friends, what we think of our Miſeries. I have ſent you ſome Reflexions on the King's <hi>Declaration;</hi> I hope you will, in requital, let me know your thoughts of it, after you have perus'd them.</p>
            <p>It does not at all reſemble thoſe Edicts which <hi>Tiberius</hi> ſent to the Senate of <hi>Rome.</hi> They were
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Verba perpauca, &amp; ſenſu permodeſto,</hi> Tacit. <hi>Annal.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſhort and modeſt,</hi> this <hi>long</hi> and <hi>extravagant.</hi> I could eaſily forgive its firſt fault, conſidering the vaſt number of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulations that were to be cram'd into it; but I can by no means bear the Second; as much as I have been accuſtom'd to the lofty ſtile of thoſe Edicts that have been publiſh'd ſince the beginning of the War, and of the Circulatory Letters that are ſent from time to time to the Biſhops, to Order <hi>Te Deum</hi> to be Sung for the taking of ſome Town, or gaining of a Victory. Theſe great words, <hi>The glory of the State; the Proſperity with which Heaven has bleſt our Reign; the Powers of</hi> Europe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57302:18"/>
               <hi>United together, to carry on an unjuſt War againſt us; the Obſtinacy of our Enemies, who ſeem inſenſible of their Loſſes, and of the Miſery of their Subjects; the unexhauſtible Power of</hi> France, <hi>when manag'd by a skilful Hand; the ſure Funds that we poſſeſs in the Hearts of our Subjects, and in their Zeal for the Service of their Sovereign, and for the glory of the</hi> French <hi>Nation.</hi> Theſe ſeemingly Fine, and ſtudied ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions are very unſutable to the preſent poſture of the King's Affairs. They are meer huffing <hi>Rhodomonta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does,</hi> which may caſt a Miſt before the Eyes of the dull and unthinking croud; but they will appear ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous to the judicious and conſidering part of Mankind.</p>
            <p>You will be of the ſame opinion, if you will give your ſelf the trouble to examine with me, what all theſe magnificent expreſſions can be reaſonably ſuppos'd to ſignifie. What is that <hi>Glory of the State which has excited the envy of the Potentates of</hi> Europe? Might it not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd from hence, that we have enjoy'd ſo much happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſince the King began to Reign, and have liv'd in ſo great an abundance of all things, and in ſo ptofound a Peace, that our Neighbours, jealous of the happineſs and riches of <hi>France,</hi> had united themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt her, and were come with a deſign to lay waſt our Provinces, ſet Fire to our Houſes and Caſtles, and raiſe our Cities, meerly becauſe they could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the vexations and mortifying ſight of a People that enjoy'd more freedom and Plenty, and liv'd more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly than all the other Nations of <hi>Europe?</hi> If this was the caſe, the King might indeed complain, and juſtly too, that the <hi>glory of his State,</hi> that is, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of all his Subjects, had <hi>rais'd the envy of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates of</hi> Europe, <hi>and that they had united themſelves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to carry on an unjuſt War againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beſides that our Neighbours are not capable of ſuch baſe and inhuman deſigns, the King has been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57302:19"/>careful not to give them the leaſt occaſion to envy the happinsſs of thoſe who live under his Dominion. <hi>England, Germany,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> have ſeen the Trade of <hi>France</hi> ruin'd, the People over-loaded with Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Provinces drain'd of Men and Money, and the King's Subjects force'd to leave their Native Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to ſeek their Bread in the remoteſt corners of the Univerſe. But far from <hi>envying</hi> the happineſs and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the <hi>French</hi> Nation, our generous Neighbours have damented our misfortunes, and to the utmoſt of their Power aſſiſted thoſe that came to implore their Help and Protection.</p>
            <p>'Tis a great while ſince we forgot the proper ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of certain words; the <hi>glory of the State,</hi> that is, according to our modern Phraſeology, the Pride and Haughtineſs of the King; to <hi>love the Publick good,</hi> that is, to furniſh His Majeſty with means to ſatisfie his Luxury and Ambition. But can you imagine, that the <hi>Engliſh, Germans,</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> would take ſuch a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Alarm at theſe improvements and alterations of our Language. They might indeed laugh at the folly of the <hi>French,</hi> who fancy that the Power of a King that oppreſſes them, is the <hi>glory of their State</hi> and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: But I durſt ſwear that they were never jealous of our pretended happineſs, ſo long as the King continued to place all his Glory, and that of the Nation in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Verſailles</hi> the moſt magnificent Palace in the World, in burying ſeveral Millions in that proud Structure, in ſquandering away his Treaſures on Caſcades and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-works, in throwing away the lives of a prodigious number of his beſt Soldiers, to alter the courſe of the River <hi>Eure,</hi> and in reducing the Noblemen that were in his Service to Beggery, by a forc'd extravagancy in Cloths, Horſes, and Equipage. So long, I ſay, as the King's Ambition aſpir'd not to higher objects than theſe,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57302:19"/>'tis very probable that his Neighboring Potentates might condemn his Pride, bewail the blindneſs of the Lords and Gentlemen of <hi>France,</hi> who conſum'd their Fortunes to ſo little purpoſe, and pity thoſe Wretches that were ſtarv'd to maintain ſo extravagant a Luxury: but I am confident, that they had not the leaſt intentions to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine together againſt <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far I dare undertake for thoſe Princes, but no farther: For without doubt they were otherwiſe affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than I have repreſented them hitherto, when they beheld the taking of <hi>Strasburg</hi> with ſeveral other Places of importance, and the pretended Acquiſition of <hi>Caſal,</hi> to the prejudice of the lawful Heirs of the Houſe of <hi>Muntua;</hi> when they ſaw <hi>Fort Lewis</hi> and the Citadel of <hi>Hunningen</hi> built to curb the <hi>Swiſs</hi> Cantons, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Princes of <hi>Germany;</hi> a project laid to enſlave <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and render it dependant on the Court of <hi>France,</hi> Sovereigns treated with the utmoſt contempt; the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Spain,</hi> and the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> chain'd at the feet of a Statue which was erected at <hi>Paris,</hi> by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant flatterer; and above a Hundred and fifty thouſand Men ready upon the firſt occaſion, either to attack <hi>Germany,</hi> or ſeize on the reſt of the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> This, Sir, is that pretended <hi>glory of the State,</hi> that has excited, not the <hi>Envy,</hi> but the indignation and juſt Revenge of the Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> had for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Years, been juſtly eſteem'd the moſt Potent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick in <hi>Europe.</hi> They enjoy'd all the bleſſings of a profound Peace; Arts flouriſh'd among them; their Trade furniſh'd them with great abundance of Money, and of all the conveniencies of Life; and the People were ſo highly ſatisfied with the eaſineſs of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57302:20"/>that the ſaying of
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rem difficillimam aſſecuti ſunt, ut illis ne voto quidem op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſit.</hi> Tacit. <hi>de moribus</hi> Germanorum.</note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> concerning the ancient <hi>Germans</hi> might have been apply'd to them. Even their beſt Friends could not have made a wiſh to their advantage; and they had nothing to deſire of God, but that he would ſuffer them long to enjoy ſo bleſt and peaceful a Life. The <hi>glory of their State</hi> was <hi>Real</hi> and <hi>Solid</hi> glory. <hi>Denmark</hi> ow'd its Liberty to them; and they had ſtopt the Kings Progreſs in the <hi>Spaniſh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands</hi> by Negotiating that <hi>Triple-League</hi> which mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified <hi>France</hi> ſo effectually. All <hi>Europe</hi> own'd that they had Reaſon to ſecure their own Liberty by keeping ſo troubleſom and Ambitious a Neighbour at a diſtance from their Frontiers; and praiſed their generouſity for protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Minor</hi> Prince againſt the unjuſt Attacks of ſo Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent an Enemy.</p>
            <p>There needed no more to incenſe the King againſt them, nor could his Wrath be appeas'd without declar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a War under pretext of the <hi>ill ſatisfaction</hi> which the States had given to the Court of <hi>France.</hi> Theſe are the very words which the King makes uſe of in a Letter which he wrote to them a little before. All the World was ſurpriz'd at the ſtrangeneſs of a Phraſe which they had never heard before: Theſe two Words were perfect ſtrangers to one another, and People could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear laughing at the odd figure which they made at their firſt meeting. But whence proceeded this <hi>ill ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction?</hi> We are told that it was caus'd by I know not what <hi>Medal,</hi> which bore the following Inſcription, <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertis Legibus &amp; Sacris: defenſis exteris Regibus; vindicatâ per orbem Chriſtianum Marium libertate. Egregiâ Pace vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute armorum partâ.</hi> You know what a pother the Court
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57302:20"/>made about this <hi>Inſcription:</hi> How inſolent they are, ory'd our flatterers? Could the <hi>Romans</hi> have ſpoken otherwiſe after the Deſtruction of <hi>Numantium</hi> and <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all, I profeſs I cannot ſee the leaſt Reaſon that could provoke them to make ſuch a hideous noiſe: For there is nothing expreſs'd by theſe words, but what is undeniably true. Had not the <hi>States General of the United Provinces</hi> oblig'd <hi>Spain</hi> to conclude a Peace with them? Had they not aſſerted their Laws and Religion by force of Arms; And had they not preſerv'd Liberty of Trade and of Navigation? The Inſcription of this Medal is infinitely more modeſt and exactly true, than any of thoſe that are to be ſeen at <hi>Verſeilles,</hi> the <hi>Town-Houſe,</hi> the <hi>Place des Victoires,</hi> the Gates of <hi>Paris,</hi> and thoſe Citadels that have been built in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. But ſuppoſe that there had been really ſome fault in the Inſcription, could that be a ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the King to ſet all <hi>Europe</hi> on Fire, to deſtroy above Two hundred thouſand Men, to lay waſte more than Fifty Leagues of Land, and to ruin his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? Confeſs with me, Sir, that the King had more Reaſon to complain of the indiſcretion of his Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for giving him <hi>ill ſatisfaction,</hi> when they made him ſay, That <hi>the glory of</hi> France <hi>has Excited the envy of the Allies;</hi> ſince it may be very eaſily prov'd, that the King himſelf was jealous of the true and ſolid glory of a Neighbouring Republick, and that his Vexation and Spite <hi>excited</hi> him to kindle a bloody War, which his brace of Hiſtorians, by their own confeſſion, are not able to juſtifie.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Quis tuler it</hi> Gracchos <hi>de ſeditone querentes?</hi>
            </q>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57302:21"/>
            <p> However, in the opinion of our flatterers, it cannot be deny'd, that <hi>Heaven has bleſt</hi> the King's Reign with ſuch an uninterrupted courſe of <hi>Proſperity,</hi> that his Neighbours have been mov'd with Jealouſy. Theſe words, <hi>Proſperity</hi> and the <hi>bleſſings of Heaven</hi> are very equivocal, and their true meaning is not unfrequently mistaken. A happy crime uſurps the name of <hi>Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> and the Fortunate unjuſtly fancy themſelves to be the favourites of Heaven. 'Tis the Language of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> that the <hi>Proſperity</hi> with which Heaven had bleſt the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Empire, <hi>excited the Envy</hi> of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Potentates that join'd together to carry on an unjuſt War</hi> againſt the <hi>Grand Signior.</hi> What is the meaning of all this, but that God in his juſt Anger againſt his People, has ſuffered thoſe <hi>Infidels</hi> to take advantage of our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and of the weakneſs of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Princes, and to lay waſte the beſt Provinces in <hi>Europe?</hi> Thoſe who are call'd Conquerors, are uſually but the <hi>Rods of God,</hi> whom he makes uſe of to ſcourge both their Subjects and their Neighbours. He <hi>bleſſes their Reign,</hi> as he bleſt of old the Reigns of <hi>Sennacherib, Nebucbadnezzar, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet II,</hi> and <hi>Solyman.</hi> But the Day of the Lord will come, when he ſhall viſit the Pride of the ſtout Hearts of the Kings of <hi>Aſſur</hi> and <hi>Babylon:</hi> He will alſo raiſe up a new Warriour, and ſend forth his <hi>Anointed</hi> and his <hi>Shepherd,</hi> who ſhall deliver and gather together his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſt People, and break to pieces the Rod which God took up in the Day of his Indignation, to puniſh our Sins, and ſcourge us for our back-ſlidings.</p>
            <p>Be not afraid, Sir, I beſeech you, that I intend to turn Prophet. Only give me leave to ſay, that we may then, and not till then, conclude, that God has truly <hi>bleſt the King's Reign,</hi> when we ſhall ſee that God has taken him by the Hand to deſtroy the Nations of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57302:21"/>Infidels, and to diſarm the Enemies of the name of Chriſt; when we ſhall perceive that the Almighty marches at the head of our Armies to make the King the reſtorer of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and repairer of the Ruins of the Temple of God. The Preachers of the Goſpel, to the ſhame of our Age be it ſpoken; are the King's great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt flatterers, and but too often have the baſeneſs to tell the King to his Face, that he is, what he ought, and we wiſh him to be. But we have the pleaſure to ſee them publickly contradicted by the <hi>Popes</hi> themſelves. 'Tis well known, that at <hi>Rome</hi> they are ſo far from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the King to be a Prince whom God has won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully rais'd up for the Honour and Deliverance of his Church, that they ſpeak there of the Wars which he has kindled as they do at <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Madrid,</hi> and Thank God for his Conqueſts and Victories no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than they do at <hi>London</hi> and at the <hi>Hague.</hi> Do the King's Miniſters imagine that we are ignorant of the true ſentiments of the Pope and Court of <hi>Rome?</hi> and have they not made the King a publick Jeſt to all the World, by making him ſay with ſo much confidence, that God has <hi>bleſt his Reign,</hi> and Crown'd him with his greateſt favours.</p>
            <p>But we ought to do Juſtice to all Mankind; let us therefore acknowledge to the Honour of the <hi>Emperor,</hi> that God does viſibly protect that Prince, and that he has lately wrought ſignal Miracles for him. The <hi>Turks</hi> had beſieged his Capital City, and he ſaw himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an ace of loſing the greateſt part of his Hereditary Provinces. We all trembled for him; but God ſtruck the <hi>Viſier</hi> with a Spirit of Infatuation. The <hi>King of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the <hi>Duke of Lorrain</hi> had time to come to the relief of <hi>Vienna</hi> with a Potent Army; the <hi>Turk</hi> loſt his beſt Troops, and the <hi>Emperor</hi> in leſs than Five Years,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57302:22"/>regain'd almoſt all that which had coſt the Turks above an Age to Conquer in the Kingdom of <hi>Hungary.</hi> What was the countenance of our Court during the ſiege of <hi>Vienna;</hi> you were aſham'd of it as well as I, and you ſpoke of it with Indignation. They appear'd very well pleas'd with the <hi>Emperors</hi> misfortunes; they expected impatiently the return of the Courrier, who they hop'd would bring the good News of the Surrender of that City, and were even making Preparations for the Reception of the Deputies of the <hi>Germans,</hi> who, they concluded, would come to implore the King's Aſſiſtance. The King had an Army ready to march into <hi>Germany,</hi> and thought to make himſelf Maſter of that Countrey under pretext of aſſiſting it. But the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vienna</hi> at once broke the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the <hi>Court</hi> and of the <hi>Divan,</hi> and overthrew all their Projects. And thoſe well-appointed Troops that were deſign'd for <hi>Germany,</hi> were imploy'd on the Projects of <hi>Maintenon,</hi> where the greateſt part of them loſt their lives.</p>
            <p>God continued ſtill more and more to bleſs the Juſtice of the <hi>Emperor's</hi> Arms. He made great Progreſſes in the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> part of <hi>Hungary:</hi> He retook <hi>Belgrade,</hi> and advanc'd even as far as <hi>Nicopoli.</hi> Is it not clear beyond exception, that this remarkable courſe of <hi>Proſperity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the Envy</hi> of the King, which engag'd him in <hi>an unjuſt War</hi> againſt a Prince that was buſied in repulſing the common Enemy of the Chriſtian Religion. At the ſame time that the Court was giving Orders to demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Churches of our <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> ſhe was labouring to find out ſome colourable pretext to hinder the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror from turning the <hi>Moſquees</hi> of <hi>Hungary,</hi> into <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Churches.</hi> And what an impious piece of Villany was this? At laſt the buſineſs of <hi>Cologne</hi> furniſh'd her with
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57302:22"/>the pretext that ſhe deſir'd, but it was certainly a very bad one: For what right had the King to interpoſe in the Election of an <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Cologne?</hi> and becauſe he had an itching deſire to ſeize on the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> he took the advantage of a pretended right of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> to the Eſtates of the late <hi>Elector Palatine</hi> her Brother.</p>
            <p>Immediately an Army was ſent to invade <hi>Germany:</hi> The <hi>Dauphin</hi> took <hi>Philipsbourg;</hi> and the Cities of <hi>Mentz, Worms, Spire, Manheim,</hi> and <hi>Heidelberg,</hi> with ſeveral other places ſurrendred without Reſiſtance. God uſually <hi>bleſſes</hi> ſuch Atttempts; for he does not always work Miracles to defend us againſt an Enemy that breaks Truces and Treaties of Peace confirm'd with the moſt ſolemn Oaths, to aſſault us unprepar'd. When I ſay that God <hi>bleſſes</hi> ſuch Attempts, you cannot miſtake my Meaning; 'tis plain, that I ſpeak in the Style of the Court, where 'tis alſo ſaid in the ſame ſenſe, that God <hi>bleſt</hi> His Majeſty's Arms, when he broke the Peace of the <hi>Pyrenees</hi> to invade the Dominions of a <hi>Minor</hi> Prince, who rely'd on the Faith of a Treaty made with <hi>Spain,</hi> or when he ruſh'd like an impetuous Deluge upon the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> who never deſign'd to give him the leaſt <hi>ill ſatisfaction.</hi> Theſe are the glorious Exploits of <hi>Lewis the Great,</hi> this is that courſe of <hi>Proſperity with which God has bleſt His Reign;</hi> this is that which has <hi>excited the Envy of the Potentates of</hi> Europe, <hi>and engag'd them in an unjuſt War againſt him.</hi> Let us examine theſe laſt words, I beſeech you; a little Attention will ſerve to diſcover the ridiculouſneſs of them.</p>
            <p>'Tis not my Buſineſs to draw up a <hi>Manifeſto</hi> for the Allies; and they are able enough to demonſtrate the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of their Arms without my Aſſiſtance. But ſince we have begun to examine the Preface of the King's <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57302:23"/>let us proceed to enquire, Whether the Author of it could ſay, with the leaſt ſhadow of Reaſon, That the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> are combin'd together to <hi>carry on an unjuſt War againſt</hi> France? In the firſt place, 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that no Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> has invaded <hi>France</hi> ſince the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty; But how many Irruptions has our King made into the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>United Netherlands, Germany</hi> and the Dominions of the Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> And the reſt of the Confederates have only put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a poſture of Defence, or aſſiſted their injur'd Allies. So that theſe ſeems to be a prejudication in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the <hi>Confederates.</hi> The King always begun the War, but the queſtion is, whether he had ever examin'd the Juſtice of his Cauſe before God, or made it appear to Judicious and dſintereſſed Perſons? If he has done neither, he ſtands Condemn'd before God and Men, for robbing his Neighbours, anſwerable before both for all the Deſolations with which he has fill'd the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> the <hi>United Provinces, Germany, Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and guilty of the Blood of above a Million of Men? and is alſo convicted before the ſame Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, for placing his delight in ruining his own Kingdom, and reducing his Subjects to the laſt extremities of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. Does not this courſe of <hi>Proſperity,</hi> with which <hi>Heaven has bleſt the Reign</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> make you tremble when you reflect upon it, and fill you with Amazement and Horror.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Inferre bella finitimis, ac populos ſibi non moleſtos ſola reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi cupiditate conterere &amp; f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bdere, quid aliud quam grande Latrocinium nominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt.</hi> Auguſt. <hi>de civit. Dei, lib.</hi> 4. cap. 4. &amp; 6.</note> He that makes War upon his Neighbours, ſays <hi>S. Auſtin,</hi> meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſatisfie a Luſt of Dominion, and ſubdues Nations that never provok'd him is uſually extoll'd by his flatterers as a <hi>great Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror,</hi> but to ſpeak ſincerely, he is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57302:23"/>only an <hi>Illuſtrious Robber.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rem tâ Juſ itiâ quid ſunt Regna niſi ma na Latrocinia? &amp; ipſa Latrocinia quid ſunt niſi parva Regna?</note> The Captain of a band of Robbers, and the Commander of a Crew of Pyrates are <hi>little Conquerors;</hi> and a Conqueror who follows blinldy the impetuous deſires of a lawleſs Ambition, is but a <hi>great Thief.</hi> Thou Wretch, ſaid the greateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror in the World to a Pyrate that was brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, what Reaſon mov'd thee to interrupt the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Trade on the Sea? The ſame, my Lord, anſwer'd the bold Corſair, that moves you to diſturb the quiet of the whole Earth. I am a <hi>Pyrate,</hi> becauſe I am Maſter only of a ſmall Veſſel; and you are a <hi>Conqueror</hi> becauſe you Command a great Fleet.</p>
            <p>It is then an uncontroverted Truth, and receiv'd for ſuch by all Nations, that a Prince who Attacks his Neighbours only with a deſign to aggrandize himſelf and to purchaſe Glory, is in the ſight of God and Men a Robber and a Pyrate. It is not only lawful, but a Duty to make Leagues againſt him, as it is to join to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to purſue a Thief, or chaſe a Pyrate. Now, tell me, Sir, whether you could have the confidence to maintain, in a company of Honeſt and Intelligent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that the King had lawfull Reaſons to invade the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands</hi> after the Death of the late King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to enter the <hi>United Provinces</hi> with a formidable Army, to ſend his Son to <hi>Germany</hi> to take <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> and to ſeize on the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and the greateſt part of the <hi>Electorates</hi> of <hi>Triers, Mentz,</hi> and <hi>Cologne!</hi> What could you alledge to juſtifie the firſt Attempt, of which the two laſt, are fatal Conſequences? Would you have recourſe to the pretended Rights of the late Queen to <hi>Hainanlt,</hi> and <hi>Brabant?</hi> She had renounc'd them in the moſt ſolemn Treaty that has been ſeen within our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57302:24"/>and the King her Husband had ſworn upon the Holy Goſpels to obſerve all the Articles. If that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation be not good, there can be no Faith or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the World, and 'tis a folly for Princes to treat together. Let them henceforth lay down their Arms when both Parties are weary of Fighting, and reſerve a right to renew the War aſſoon as they ſhall be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to proſecute it: For ſuch Maxims would be found to be infinitely leſs pernicious than the impious Politicks of thoſe who make a mock of Religion, and ſwear by all that is moſt venerable in it, to obſerve the conditions of a Treaty which they are reſolv'd to break upon the firſt favourable occaſion. But you will perhaps ſay, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> conſtrain'd his Daughter to act againſt her true Inrereſt, and treated her with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Injuſtice. <hi>Conſtraint</hi> and <hi>Jnjuſtice,</hi> Sir! Can any Man of ſenſe make ſo ridiculous a Suppoſition? The Queen might have declar'd, that ſhe would not renounce her Right to <hi>Hainault, Brabant,</hi> and the reſt of her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Dominions; and he would have taken care to Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her to ſuch a Husband, and in ſuch a manner, as might have been moſt conducive to the Intereſt of the <hi>Spaniſh Monarchy,</hi> and to the Peace and Tranquility of <hi>Europe.</hi> But the <hi>Infanta</hi> choſe rather to be <hi>Queen</hi> of a great Nation, than to be <hi>Counteſs of Hainault,</hi> and <hi>Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of Brabant,</hi> or to preſerve a claim to a ſucceſſion which ſhe was not ſure to enjoy, as indeed ſhe never did: And with what Reaſon then could ſhe complain, of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> or <hi>Conſtraint?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus 'tis plain, that the King had not any lawful Reaſon to break the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty: And it muſt be acknowledged, that the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> acted a very Wiſe and Honourable part, when they negotiated the <hi>Tripple-League</hi> to ſtop the Progreſs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57302:24"/>of his Majeſty's Arms in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands.</hi> It was their Duty to defend a King who was their Neighbour and Ally, againſt the unjuſt Attacks of a Potent Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that threatned to diſpoſſeſs him according to the Maxim of an
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui non repellit Injuriam a ſocio, ſi poteſt, tam eſt in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tjo, quam ille qui facit. lib.</hi> 1. Offic. cap. 36.</note> ancient Father of the Church. Beſides, Prudence oblig'd them to keep at a diſtance from their Frontiers, an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince, who aſſum'd a right to interpret Treaties to his own advantage, and who, they might reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſuppoſe, would not fail ſooner or later, to make the ſame uſe of the Houſe of <hi>Burgundy</hi> to claim the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> as he then did of the Queen's Right to <hi>Hainault</hi> and <hi>Brabant.</hi> And did he not afterwards in effect revive the pretenſions of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe places that depend upon <hi>Alſatia.</hi> I confeſs that it is not juſt to make War upon a Neighbour, who-is grown too powerful, under pretext that 'tis our Intereſt to weaken him, leſt he ſhould be one Day in a condition to hurt us. But it has been always eſteem'd lawful to oppoſe a Neighbour that aggrandizes himſelf unjuſtly, or who having at the beſt but a controverted Right to certain Provinces that are in the poſſeſſion of another Prince, chuſes ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have recourſe to an open War, than to refer the difference to the Judgment of their common Allies, or other diſintereſſed States
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtum bellum quibus neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium, &amp; pia arma quibus nulla niſi in armis relinquitur ſpes.</hi> Liv. <hi>lib.</hi> 10.</note>
               <q>A Prince that is truly juſt and merciful, never makes War, but when the neceſſity of his Circumſtances, renders it unavoidable or when there are are no other means leſt to preſerve or put himſelf in poſſeſſion of that which properly belongs to him.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57302:25"/>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Clementia alieno Sanguini tanquam ſuo parcit, &amp; ſcit homini non eſſe homine prodigé utendum.</hi> Seneca. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 87.</note> He is as tender of the Blood of others as of his own, and he is ſenſible that a Man ought not lightly to hazard the Lives of his Fellow Creatures.</q> But theſe Maxims of equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Heathens,</hi> are utterly unknown at the Court of the <hi>moſt Chriſtian</hi> King.</p>
            <p>Nor are they better acquainted there, with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment that Chriſt left us, to <hi>forgive Injuries.</hi> Would any Prince that had the leaſt ſenſe of Chriſtianity, have preſum'd, in the face of all <hi>Europe,</hi> to declare War againſt the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> under the pretext of I know not what <hi>ill ſatisfaction</hi> that they had given him? For what had they done to provoke his Anger? If it proceeded from the care which they took to negotiate the <hi>Tripple-League,</hi> it was certainly very unjuſt; ſince the <hi>States</hi> acted in that Affair, like Wiſe and Chriſtian Politicians. Or was it the above mentioned <hi>Medal</hi> that occaſioned all this <hi>ill ſatisfaction?</hi> Was there any thing in it that was not exactly true, or that could give him the leaſt cauſe of Offence? But ſuppoſe that it had been injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to him:
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Magni animi eſt injurias in ſummâ potentia pati, nec quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam eſt glorioſius Principe impuné laeſo</hi> Senec. <hi>de clem</hi> l. 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note>
               <q>True magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, ſays a Pagan Philoſopher, conſiſts in ſuffering Injuries even when we are in the height of Proſperity: And a Prince is never more truly great and glorious, than when he leaves theſe unpuniſh'd, who have moſt highly offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</q> Beſides, the King was further oblig'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give that pretended Injury, becauſe the <hi>States</hi> were not only ſorry that their <hi>Medal</hi> had diſpleas'd him, but took all poſſible care to ſuppreſs it, in ſo much, that it is no where extant, but in the Cabinets of ſome cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Perſons.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57302:25"/>
            <p> The Court of <hi>France</hi> is not ſo obſervant of the Rules of Decency: For though the Proud and Inſolent Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Gates of <hi>St. Denis</hi> and <hi>St. Martin</hi> had given offence to the greateſt Sovereigns in <hi>Europe;</hi> they were ſo far from offering them ſatisfaction, that they ſuffer'd a Courtier, who would have certainly paſt for the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Fool in the World, if he had not been too well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the weak ſide of his Prince, to out do the groſſeſt flatteries of the Provoſt of the Merchants and <hi>Echevins</hi> of <hi>Paris.</hi> He was even recompenſed for erecting a Statue, at the Feet of which, the King's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Enemies were repreſented in ſo unworthy a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that 'tis impoſſible to look upon it without Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: And the moſt celebrated Wits of the <hi>French Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy,</hi> were excited in emulation of one another, to make Inſcriptions for that ridiculous Statue, which never any reaſonable Perſon could Read without Indignation.</p>
            <p>Or was it the <hi>Dutch Gazettiers</hi> Wit that gave the King this <hi>ill ſatisfaction?</hi> We are aſſur'd by certain Authors, whoſe Books were Printed at <hi>Paris,</hi> with His Majeſty's Priviledge; that this did not a little contribute to the Declaration of War; 'Tis ſtrange, that ſuch able Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as <hi>M. le Tellier,</hi> and <hi>M. Colbert,</hi> ſhould not have repreſented to the King,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Tulere iſta &amp; reliquere; haud facile dixerim modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione magis an Sapientia</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus <hi>Annal.</hi> 4.</note> that the Wiſdom as well as the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of <hi>Julius</hi> and <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> never appear'd with more Luſtre than by neglecting thoſe that writ againſt them. You know, Sir, that Works of that nature are
<note n="*" place="margin">Spreta exoleſcunt, ſi iraſcare, agnita videntur.</note> wont to fall of themſelves, when they are neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; but when he whom they Attack, grows Angry at their Inſolence, he gives the World occaſion to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there is too much Truth in the reproaches
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57302:26"/>that are faſten'd upon him. <hi>Tacitus</hi> has a judicious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark to this purpoſe, which ought to moderate the Heat of thoſe who meditate Revenge againſt an Author of a biting Jeſt, or an ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Satyr.
<note n="*" place="margin">Punitis ingeniis, gliſcit authoritas.</note> The moſt proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way to advance the credit of ſuch a Book, is to cauſe it to be burnt, or to chaſtiſe its Author.
<note n="*" place="margin">Qui ſaevitiâ uſi ſunt, niſi dedecus ſibi, at que illis gloriam peperêre.</note> And thoſe Princes who uſe ſuch rigorous Methods, do a far greater Injury to their own Reputation, than to the Author of the piece that offends them. The Book runs through all Hands, and People are curious to know the Reaſon that procur'd the Author ſo ſevere a Treatment. Judge then how great the curioſity of our Poſterity will be, and how eagerly they will examine thoſe bitter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions of the <hi>Dutch Gazettier,</hi> which incenſed the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Monarch in the World to ſuch a degree, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not puniſh the Author, he marched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the Head of a Hundred Thouſand Men to deſtroy the Countrey where theſe Satyrs were Printed.</p>
            <p>The Inhabitants of <hi>Antioch</hi> having broken to pieces the Statue of the Emperor <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> he reſolv'd to raze that ungrateful and ſeditious City. Immediatly the Biſhop <hi>Flavian</hi> went to appeaſe the incens'd Mind of that Prince, whoſe indignation was far more juſt than that of <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> againſt the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces.
<note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſtom. <hi>homil.</hi> 4. <hi>ad po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pul</hi> Antloch.</note> The glory of Monarchs,</hi> my Lord, ſaid the Prelate to <hi>Theodoſius, conſiſts not ſo much in beating their Enemies, as in ſubduing their Paſſions. Victory is not wholly your own; for your Officers and Soldiers claim a part of it; but in an Action of Wiſdom and Goodneſs you have no Companions, and that is a Trophy to which none
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57302:26"/>but your ſelf has a Right to pretend. 'Tis not enough that you have Conquer'd the</hi> Barbarians, <hi>if you do not alſo Conquer your own Anger. Show thoſe Infidels, that no Power on Earth is able to ſtand in oppoſition to</hi> Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Sovereign Maſter by pardoning the Faults of your Brethren, that, at the great and terrible Day of the Lord, he may look upon your Errors with the Eye of a Father, rather then of a Judge, and that you may receive the ſame For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs from him, that you have granted to others.</hi> Why do not thoſe whoſe Dignity and Function oblige them to inform the King of His Duty, ſpeak to him with equal Freedom. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> had more Reaſon to be <hi>ill ſatisfied</hi> with the inſolency of his own Subjects, than His Majeſty had to be Angry with the <hi>States.</hi> The overthrowing of a Statue was a far more provoking In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, than the reverſe of a Medal coin'd by ſtrangers, or the Jeſts of a diſown'd Gazettier. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> deſign'd to deſtroy a Seditious City; <hi>Lewis</hi> endeavoured to ruine entire Provinces. Ought not the managers of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to have repreſented to him, that ſo cruel a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge would not fail to fill the Hearts of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with Horror, and give occaſion of ſcandal to the <hi>Infidels.</hi> Nevertheleſs, inſtead of Offering him ſuch good Advice, the Biſhops and Preachers employed all their Eloquence, either in magnifying his Victories, or in demonſtrating even to himſelf, that he was the greateſt and moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Monarch in the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>Do not tell me, that the King undertook the War againſt a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> State, a People who make it their boaſt to be the Protectors of <hi>Hereſy</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> and ſpread it through the other parts of the World. For beſides, that a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ought to forgive <hi>Hereticks</hi> and even <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels,</hi> as well as <hi>Catholicks,</hi> I dare aſſure you, that a Zeal for Religion was not the motive of that War. No ſooner
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57302:27"/>had <hi>Germany</hi> declar'd War againſt us, but we deteſted thoſe very Cities, whoſe Churches <hi>Cardinal de Bouillon</hi> had bleſt and reconcil'd with ſo much Pomp and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. I know not whether it was a ſentiment of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion that made the <hi>Mareſchal de Belfonds</hi> delay the Execution of the Orders that were ſent to him, to leave thoſe places, where the Catholick Religion was re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed; but I am aſſur'd that the Court was very much diſſatisfied with him for it.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, we ſee, that the Pretext for the <hi>Dutch</hi> War was even leſs ſpecious than that which was formerly made uſe of for the War with <hi>Spain.</hi> One of my Friends was ſo throughly convinc'd of the unjuſtneſs of this War, that he left the Service. Do not fancy that he was a <hi>Huguenot,</hi> you know him, he is a good <hi>Catholick:</hi> And you may remember that at the ſame time, the <hi>Mareſchal de Scomberg,</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Gentlemen were in the Army. I had the curioſity to ask my Friend what made him leave a good Poſt at a time when Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments were ſo much courted by others. He told me that his Conſcience would not permit him to ſerve the King in a manifeſtly unjuſt War. Why do you trouble your ſelf with thoſe things, reply'd I; 'tis the King's buſineſs, and that of his Miniſters to examine that Controverſy, and Obedience is the Subject's only part. You tell me nothing, ſaid he, but what I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd before, I had Read <hi>Grotius de jure belli &amp; pacis,</hi> who has convinc'd me that I ought not to ſerve my Prince in a War, which I know to be unjuſt. Read that Book, added he, and you will be of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>At that time I was taken up with other Matters, and contented my ſelf with doing what I ſaw others do before me. But after the Peace of <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> I began
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57302:27"/>to reflect upon what my Friend ſaid to me, and reſolv'd to conſult the Book that he recommended to me. No ſooner had I caſt my Eyes upon it, but I obſerv'd with pleaſure, that it was dedicated to the late King <hi>Lewis XIII.</hi> The moderation of that Learned Man, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by all the World, and 'tis alſo well known that he was a great Friend to the Soveraign Authority of Kings: And yet, in the firſt place he maintains, that
<note place="margin">* <hi>Si aut ad deliberationem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibentur, aut libera ipſis optio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datur militandi aut quieſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, eaſdem regulas ſequi de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, quas illi, qui ſuopte ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio pro ſe &amp; pro aliis bella ſuſcipiunt.</hi> Grotius <hi>de jure belli &amp; pacis, lib.</hi> 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 26.</note> when a Prince asks the Advice of his Subjects concerning a War, which he deſigus to undertake, or gives them Liberty to chuſe, whether they will ſerve in his Armies, or ſtay at home in Peace; 'tis their Duty to follow the ſame Maxims which their Sovereign ought to obſerve before he begin the War: That is, that they ought not to adviſe him to undertake the War without juſt and and indiſpenſible Reaſons; and if he perſiſt in his reſolution, they cannot without a crime offer him their aſſiſtance, to ſhed innocent Blood. What can there be alledged againſt ſo clear a Deciſion? And indeed it makes me tremble, as oft as I think of it, not for the King's Miniſters, ſince theſe Gentlemen are not wont to conſult either the light of Reaſon, or Rules of the Goſpel, but for an infinite number of People, who put themſelves into His Majeſty's Service, without conſidering what they do, and oftentimes even againſt the Dictates of their Conſcience, which tells them that the War is unjuſt.</p>
            <p>But perhaps the Nobility, who never march, but when the <hi>Arrier-ban</hi> is ſummon'd, are more excuſeable. Let
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57302:28"/>us hear what the ſame Author adds.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Si edicitur ipſis ut militent, quod fieri ſolet, ſiquidem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtet ipſis injuſtam eſſe belli cauſam, abſtinere omnino de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. Deo potius obediendum quam hominibus</hi> &amp;c. Idem.</note> If the Prince, ſays he, by a poſitive command, ordain his Subjects to follow him to the War, they are oblig'd to diſobey his Orders, when they are convinc'd, that the War is unjuſt. For 'tis an uncontrovert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maxim among <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> as well as among <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that <hi>it is better to obey God than Men.</hi> This de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of <hi>Grotius</hi> furniſh'd me with this reflection, that the ancient Cuſtom of <hi>France</hi> and other <hi>European</hi> Nations, of which I took Notice in the Letter that I had the Honour to write to you about the beginning of this Month, was grounded upon very good Reaſons. The Lords and Gentlemen were not obliged to ſerve the King till after the War was decreed in the meeting of the States General of the Kingdom: The Reaſon is plain; it was fit that an Affair of ſuch vaſt importance on which the Lives of ſo many Men did depend, and which might ruin whole Nations, ſhould be gravely debated, and diligently examin'd both by the Prince himſelf who was to undertake it, and thoſe who were to ſerve him.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall the Subjects do, when the Juſtice of the War in which they are like to be engag'd, appears only doubtful to them? It may ſeem perhaps a needleſs piece of curioſity, to ſtart Caſes that we never had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to experience, 'tis certain, that <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> never undertook a War that was not manifeſtly unjuſt. Yet there may have been ſome Perſons who imagin'd that the late Queen's claim was at leaſt diſputable. <hi>France</hi> publiſh'd whole Volumes to demonſtrate the Juſtice of her Pretenſions, and <hi>Spain</hi> anſwer'd them. This might probably diſquiet the minds of ſome <hi>French
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57302:28"/>men,</hi> that were not able to decide the Controverſie: Now the Queſtion is, whether ſuch Perſons were oblig'd in Conſcience to Fight under the King's Standards. <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> acknowledges that there are ſome Lawyers that hold the Affirmative, but poſitively declares himſelf for the Negative, which he confirms with a Reaſon that to me ſeems to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Qui dubitat contemplativè, debet judicio activo eligere par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem tutiorem, eſt autem pars tutior abſtinere bello. Laudan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> Eſſeni <hi>quod inter alia ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarent non necituros ſe cuiquam ne ſi juberentur quidem; Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatores eorum</hi> Pythagorei, <hi>qui</hi> Jamblico <hi>teſte, bello abſtine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, cauſa additâ quia bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum caedes imperat.</hi>
               </note> In all dubious Caſes, ſays he, A Wiſe Man always chuſes the ſafeſt ſide: Now 'tis certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſafeſt way to abſtain from an Action that may engage us to injure our Neighbour, and ſhed Human Blood. This Book has been done into <hi>French,</hi> and the Tranſlation dedicated to the King and would to God that not only His Majeſty, but his Miniſters of State, the Nobility and Clergy would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſome few Hours on Reading that piece with At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. There would not be ſo much Blood ſhed, ſo many Nations laid Waſte, and ſuch a vaſt number of Perſons reduc'd to Beggery. The Preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel would ceaſe to extol thoſe Generals, whoſe Virtue for the moſt part, conſiſts in nothing elſe, but in ſtifling the gnawing Remonſtrances of an awak'd Conſcience, to ſerve the abominable Ambition of their Maſter. But how ſhall private Perſons be inform'd whether the King had lawful Reaſons to undertake the War, unleſs by his <hi>Manifeſtos</hi> and <hi>Declarations?</hi> Thus my Friend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that the King had taken up Arms againſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> meerly to be reveng'd upon them, for the <hi>ill ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction</hi> that they had given him, he choſe rather to quit an advantagious Poſt, than to expoſe himſelf to the reproaches of his Conſcience, by continuing to
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57302:29"/>ſerve in a War which he believed to be unjuſt. If they who ſerve in our Armies had imitated the Example of my generous Friend, if they had examin'd the King's <hi>Manifeſtoes,</hi> they would not have been ſo acquainted with their own and their Countries Intereſt. Good God! Will the <hi>French</hi> Nation never learn Wiſdom? Will they never be weary of being led to the Army like a pack of Hounds to a Hunting-match? Will they always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to ſacrifice their Fortunes, their Liberty and their Life, meerly to give their King the pleaſure of aſſuming the Title of <hi>Lewis the Great?</hi> But 'tis time to proceed to the conſequences of the <hi>Dutch War;</hi> and to take a view of the glaring part of the King's Life.</p>
            <p>The taking of above <hi>Forty</hi> Towns in the compaſs of one Campaign, the Surrender of <hi>Maeſtricht</hi> after a Siege of Thirteen Days, the Conqueſt of <hi>Cambray, S. Omer, Ypres,</hi> and <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> the Battels of <hi>Caſſel</hi> and <hi>Senef,</hi> and the diſadvantageous Peace which the Allies were forc'd to make, may ſerve indeed for materials to ſtuff a flattering <hi>Panegyrick</hi> or <hi>Inſcription,</hi> but all together will not amount to one ſingle Argument, to prove that God has <hi>bleſt the Reign</hi> of the King, and <hi>the Juſtice of his Arms.</hi> To meaſure the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of an Attempt by the <hi>Happineſs</hi> of its Succeſs, is the way to be eternally deceiv'd, and to juſtifie the blackeſt Crimes. Temporal Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity is not uſually a mark of the particular favour of Heaven. The God whom we adore, is infinitely Wiſe; He ſuffers the Righteous to be afflicted, and the Wicked to proſper in their Day. Let us adore then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable Myſteries of his Providence; and let us judge of True Merit by the Light of Reaſon, and by the Rules of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>It muſt be acknowledg'd that the King was very well ſerv'd by his Miniſters, and by the Generals of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57302:29"/>his Forces, during that War. But it was not a very ſurpriſing Accident, that a Republick that was at once aſſaulted by Land and by Sea, could not reſiſt a King that came Thundering againſt her with an Army of a Hundred thouſand Men, commanded by the two great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captains that <hi>Europe</hi> had ſeen in many Yeats before. He took <hi>Forty</hi> Towns in one Campaign, it cannot be deny'd; but was he not forced to abandon them with ſhame, as ſoon as the <hi>Imperial</hi> Army had ſeiz'd on ſome places of the <hi>Rhine? Maeſtricht</hi> was Surrendred after a Siege of Thirteen Days; a great Miracle indeed! For how could the <hi>States</hi> relieve it? The Inſcriptions on the Gates of <hi>St. Denis</hi> and <hi>St. Martin</hi> do more Honour to the <hi>States,</hi> than to the King. He broke in upon them, 'tis true, like a furious and overbearing Deluge; and they were not able to put a ſtop to his Progreſs; yet I do not believe, that all this Action gain'd him one Admirer. But that <hi>Holland,</hi> ſhould force the moſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Monarch in <hi>Europe,</hi> to abandon his unjuſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and to ſue for a Peace by offering to reſtore to them the only place that he ſtill retain'd of all that he had taken from them, is an event ſo little common and ſo full of Glory, that it will be the greateſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhment of the Hiſtory of this Age, and the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all that ſhall ſucceed it. <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> took Forty Cities, and made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Maeſtricht,</hi> after a Siege of Thirteen Days; but what was the fruit of all his Victories, and what did he retain of ſo many Conqueſts but an exhauſted Kingdom, Peopled with Beggars. Is not this the only inſtance of a Prince that was Honoured with Triumphal Arches for ruining his own Subjects.</p>
            <p>The taking of <hi>Valenciennes, Ypres,</hi> and <hi>Cambray,</hi> were Actions that had a juſter Title to the proud name of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57302:30"/>
               <hi>Conqueſts.</hi> The <hi>Empire, Spain,</hi> and the <hi>States General</hi> of the <hi>United Provinces</hi> had form'd a Confederacy againſt the King, and had often alarm'd him with Potent Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Let us do juſtice to the Merit and Experience of the late <hi>Prince,</hi> and of the <hi>Mareſchal de Turenne,</hi> who were only able to preſerve us in ſuch an Extremity. They alone merited the Honour of Statues and Triumphal Arches, and to have their Names inſcrib'd on our Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals. The pretended Glory of <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> is only a reflected Splendor, which he ows to the Valour and Experience of his ill rewarded Generals, and to the Skill and Dexterity of his Two Miniſters, one of which made it his buſineſs to find out ways to ſqueeze Money out of miſerable Wretches, while the other provided well-ſtor'd Magazines, that the King's Army might be in a condition to enter upon Action, before that of the Enemies could be drawn out of their Winter-quarters.</p>
            <p>It was certainly a very prudent Advice, that of <hi>M. de Turenne,</hi> to keep all things in a readineſs for the early opening of the Campagn. And 'twas by a careful ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance of this Maxim, that <hi>France</hi> broke the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Confederates, and obtain'd an advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Peace. But I maintain that a Prince who ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandizes himſelf meerly by ſuch Politicks, does not deſerve the name of a <hi>Conqueror.</hi> The <hi>Alexanders, Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pios, Pompeys,</hi> and <hi>Caeſars,</hi> of thoſe celebrated Glories of Antiquity, took other Methods to acquire Honour, than thoſe that are now in faſhion among our <hi>Heroes of all Seaſons.</hi> This is one of thoſe ſplendid Titles that the <hi>Sappho</hi> of our Age beſtows on the King: And you know this thought was eſteem'd very ingenious and fine. Did ever any of thoſe <hi>Summer Heroes</hi> which are plac'd ſo far beneath the <hi>Heroes of all Seaſons,</hi> content themſelves with ſeizing on a Town that could not be reliev'd; did
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57302:30"/>ever any of them forſake their Arms, immediatly after ſuch an inglorious Expedition, or Poſt back to their Miſtreſſes as ſoon as the Enemies began to appear, and leave the care of engaging with them to others?</p>
            <p>Let the Gentlemen of the <hi>French-Academy,</hi> rack their mercenary Fancies to embelliſh their fulſom Panegyricks with new <hi>Hyberboles;</hi> it will be for ever acknowledg'd by thoſe who are willing to do Juſtice to true Merit, that the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> acquir'd more ſolid Glory of the Siege of <hi>St. Omer</hi> and the Battel of <hi>Caſſel,</hi> than the King by the taking of <hi>Cambray, Ypres,</hi> and <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> and (if you pleaſe to add) <hi>Mons,</hi> and <hi>Namur.</hi> By com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of his Lines, meeting the Enemy, gaining a Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and afterwards taking the Beſieg'd Town, he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited far greater Honour, than the King by all that he perform'd before <hi>Mons</hi> and <hi>Namur.</hi> Inſtead of advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to meet the Confederate Forces that appear'd towards the end of the Siege of <hi>Mons</hi> which they could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly relieve, the King with all his jolly Troop, made haſte back to his dear <hi>Verfailles,</hi> and arriv'd there with Men and Horſes that were as freſh and unfatigu'd as thoſe that had not begun to march. The taking of this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Place was a <hi>Bleſſing from Heaven</hi> on the Providence of <hi>M. Louvois,</hi> and skill of <hi>M. de Vauban,</hi> rather than on the Valour of the King, or the <hi>Juſtice of his Arms.</hi> The next Year he took <hi>Namur,</hi> in ſight of the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Army, but he was cover'd by an Army greater than theirs, during the Siege of the Caſtle; which was an advantage that the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> had not at the Siege of <hi>St. Omer.</hi> He was forced to come out of his Lines and Fight the Enemy. An inſtance that cannot be pararel'd in all the glorious Life of <hi>Lewis the Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where ſhall we find a <hi>Homer</hi> to celebrate our new <hi>Achilles?</hi> But we may truſt that care to himſelf; he will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57302:31"/>not ſuffer future Ages to loſe ſo great an Example: he has hir'd his <hi>Chroniclers</hi> already, and carries them always about with him, that they may be Eye-witneſſes of all his Glorious Exploits. But all in vain, our Poſterity will eaſily diſcover the Truth, and pull of the diſguiſing Vizard of Flattery: And perhaps ſome Hiſtorian may luck in a Garret that will inform them after what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Lewis the Great</hi> took ſo many Towns, and gain'd all his Victories. And even I am very much afraid, that they will Read the Hiſtories of the King as we Read the Books of thoſe infamous flatterers who prais'd <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>Nero,</hi> and that they will have the ſame regard to all our <hi>Medals</hi> and <hi>Triumphal Arches</hi> that we have, to thoſe which remain of certain Ptinces, whoſe Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty we mock and deſpiſe.</p>
            <p>I have not time to ſend you my Reflexions on the preſent Was, but you may expect them by the next occaſion, Adieu.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jan.</hi> 23 1695.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57302:31"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
